<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The godly saiyngs of the old auncient faithful fathers vp on the Sacrament of the bodye and bloude of Chryste. Newlye compyled and translated oute of Latin intoo English. By Ihon Veron Senonoys.</title>
            <author>Véron, John, d. 1563.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B16192</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840959</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176398</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248565762</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 24682</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S105230</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99840959e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B16192)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176398)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 157:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The godly saiyngs of the old auncient faithful fathers vp on the Sacrament of the bodye and bloude of Chryste. Newlye compyled and translated oute of Latin intoo English. By Ihon Veron Senonoys.</title>
                  <author>Véron, John, d. 1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[128] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ihon Oswen. They be also to sell at Shrewesburye,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted the .xi. day of October. Anno. Do. 1550. At worceter :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1550]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H.</note>
                  <note>At end of colophon: Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176398:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176398:1"/>
            <p>The godly sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yngs of the old auncient faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful fathers / vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on the Sacrament of the the bodye and bloude of Chryste. New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye compyled and translated oute of Latin intoo En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish. By Ihon Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron Seno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noys.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>i. Cor. xi.</bibl>
               <p>As often as ye eate of thys breade, and drynke of thys cuppe, ye shal shew furth the lordes death tyll he come.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_names">
            <pb facs="tcp:176398:2"/>
            <head>¶ The names and times of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy doctors whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we do folow in thys lyttle treatye.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Vgustyne was borne in Carthage, &amp; was bisshoppe of Hippone, a Citie in Aphrica. He dyed in the yere of our Lorde. C C C C. xxx. when he was. lx xvi. yeres of age.</p>
            <p>¶ Ambrose was Bisshoppe of Milane, in Lombardie, being a Romaine borne, he did florisshe vnder Theodosius the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, in the yere of our Lorde. C C C. xxx.</p>
            <p>¶ Athanasius the .xix. bisshop of Alexandria, died in the yeare of our Lorde. C C C. lxxix.</p>
            <p>¶ Bede being Prieste of thys countrey of England, then cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Britaine, died in the yere of
<pb facs="tcp:176398:2"/> our lorde. D. C C. xxxii.</p>
            <p>¶ Barnard was in the yeare of our Lord. M. C. xl.</p>
            <p>¶ Chrisostome beinge bisshop of Constantinople, dyed in the yere of our lorde. C C C C. xi.</p>
            <p>¶ Fulgentius was bysshop of Ruspa, in Aphrike. Thys man did florish in all godly learning at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> time, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Trasmundus king of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Wandallians, did persecute the faithfull churche of Christe, in the yere of our Lorde. D.</p>
            <p>¶ Gelasius, fyrst of that name was bisshop of Rome .iiii. yeres and died in the yere of our lord C C C C. xcvi.</p>
            <p>¶ Hierome beinge borne in a towne of Italie, called Studō, dyed in the yere of our Lorde. C C C C. xxii.</p>
            <p>¶ Origene being born in Alex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>andria, did florysshe in the yere of our lorde. C C. lxi.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176398:3"/>
            <p> ¶ Prosper beinge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> nation of Aquitaine, was Bisshoppe of Reginum, and did florishe in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yere of our lord. C C C C. lx</p>
            <p>¶ Tertullian was of the citie of Carthage, in Aphrica, &amp; did florish in the yere of our lord C C.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>¶ The authour to the Christian readers.</head>
            <l>¶ Because I was in Fraunce, which is so wyde,</l>
            <l>Borne &amp; brought vp, &amp; not in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> English</l>
            <l>Sins my birthes dai, as other writers be</l>
            <l>Learned and taught: do I earnestlye,</l>
            <l>Now you al that in England do dwell,</l>
            <l>And professe Christ, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> euer springing wel</l>
            <l>Desyre and pray, to take in good worth,</l>
            <l>That I haue here wrought &amp; set furthe.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176398:3"/>
            <head>To the right worshypfull, Syr Ihon Yorke, Knight, treasurer of the Kinges Maiesties Mint in Southwarke, master of all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Kinges wooddes, on this syde Trente, and Shriue of the noble citie of London, Ihon Peron wissheth healthe of soule and bodye, with encrease of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyne knowledge and vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, from the heauenlye father, through our lord and Sauyoure Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>EN are wonte, for the most parte, either of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition, to attrybute to muche to the holy sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramentes, or of a lyght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and inconstancie, to attribute to little vntoo them. Whyche thing we may easly se in the historyes of the olde auncyent Iewes, which had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb facs="tcp:176398:4"/> for an high sacramente, the Arke of the lordes couenaunt, that with plain wordes, is called the lord of hostes. For in the second boke of the kinges, and .vi. <note place="margin">ii. kin .vi. cha.</note> Cha. the scripture doth testifye and saye: Dauid rising vp, went with all hys peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to fetche the Arke of God, wherup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the name of the lorde god of hostes. whiche sitteth vpon Cherubin, is called vpon. And this after y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> phrase of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues, is as muche to say, as vnto whom a name is geuen, that it should be called Iehouah, or the lord of hostes syt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon Cherubin: Thys verely was a great mistery, and an high sacrament. But when the Israelites dydde attry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to muche vntoo it, they were ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen, and subdued w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the warres of Philistyns, and the Arke also was taken and caried away into captyuitie. For so we do reade in the holy Bible, that Isra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>el was ouerthrowen before the Phily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stins, iiii. M. men of them beyng slayne. And when y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people of Israel did return into the Campe, the elders and seniours of Israel, dyd say: Why hath the lord o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowen vs this day before the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listines?
<pb facs="tcp:176398:4"/> We wyll bringe from Silo, the <note place="margin">i Sam. iiii. cha</note> Arke of the lordes couenaunt, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it maye be in the middest of vs, and saue vs from the handes of our enemyes. The people therfore dyd send to Silo, and did bring from thence the Arke of the lorde of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes, sytting vpon Cherubin. And when the Arke of the couenaunt was come in to the Campe, all Israel gaue so great a shoute, that the earth did quake. Which crie and noyse, when y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Philistines herd and had alsoo knowledge, that the Arke of the lorde was come into the Campe, they were sore afrayde, sayinge: God is come into the Campe. Wo be vntoo vs. Who shall delyuer vs from the hand of these straunge goddes. These be the god des that dyd smyte Egipt with somany plagues, yet notwythstandynge, be of a good chere, and fyght lyke men. So the Philistines did strike battaile, and Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el was discomfited, and fled euerye man intoo hys tente, and there was a greate slaughter done. For .xxx. thousande of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Isralites footemen were killed, yea, and the Arke was taken. Now haue ye herd what the Israelites did attribute vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Arke, and what misfortune both for this
<pb facs="tcp:176398:5"/> erroure, and alsoo for other synnes, they dyd then suffer and receyue of theyr e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes. For the Lorde had not gyuen therefore the Arke vnto his people, that they shoulde put theyr truste in it, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that it moughte delyuer and saue theym from the handes of theyr enemyes: but that it shoulde be a sygne and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the presence and helpe of GOD and was therefore called the Lorde of hostes, because it shoulde be a certayne testymonye and wytnesse of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunte made betwyxt God and the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple. For it dyd teffyfye that god would be presente, alwayes fauourable and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily are vntoo hys people. In the same Arke, the tables of the couenaunte were contayned and kepte, wherof it dyd get hys name, and was called the Arke of the couenaunte. Whyche when they dydde contrarywyse handle irreuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, hauynge it in lesse estymatyon then they oughte, manye more of them were slayne then when they dydde attrybute too muche vntoo it.</p>
            <p>For when the Phylystynes beynge plagued with foul diseases, had brought <note place="margin">i. Samuel .v. and .vi. Chap.</note> the Arke agayne, and restored it too the
<pb facs="tcp:176398:5"/> Israelytes, the people whyche loked in it irreuerently were slayne. For the scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture saythe: The Lorde dyd plague the Bethsemeites, because they had looked in the Arke of the lorde, and he did strike fiftye thousand and thre score and tenne men. For it was forbydden by the lawe (as it is wrytten in the boke of Numery <note place="margin">ii. king .vi. cha</note> the forthe Chapiter), that no man shuld searche or loke in the Arke of the lord of hostes, wyth prophane and irreuerente eyes. Wherefore in the exposytyon and ministring of the sacramentes, that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye whyche is prescribed in the worde of GOD, and the scryptures muste of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessytye be folowed. But nowe let vs cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pare thys worlde wyth those auncyente tymes, and we shall in thys matter fynd theym in all thynges lyke. For thou shalte fynde some whyche attrybute all <note place="margin">As if a manne forsaking pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>digalitie shuld fal into beget<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly nigardship or forsakynge vngodlynesse, shulde fal into superstition.</note> maner of thynges too the Sacramentes and agayne there be some other whych doo attrybute nothinge at all vnto them Soo that in thys poynte, that whyche the heathen Poete Flaccus doth wryte proueth moste trewe. Fooles whyles they doo flye from one synne, they doo runne intoo an other contrarye vyce.
<pb facs="tcp:176398:6"/> For there be many whiche doo adscribe vnto the sacramentes, grace, iustyficatiō health and saluation most seruillye, as. S Angustine doth say, worshipping and ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerating the signes, for the thinges, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che by the signes are signified. Such mē haue, and not without sacrilege and spy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual thefte, taken a waie from the faith full, the cuppe of the lordes bloude. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides that, all men doo knowe that they <note place="margin">Ye shall rede in their masse bookes howe thei said Mas for mesel swin for scalde hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. &amp;c.</note> haue abused the lordes supper too heale diseases, to driue away foule spirites, too make fayre weather, and to many other vile and filthy things. And agayne how they vtterly subuerting the outward sig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, dyd contende and affirme, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther breade nor wyne did remaine, but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body and bloud of the lord onely. Of the whyche maner of beynge in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente miraculouslye, they haue dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted manye thynges, whyche thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles neuer knewe, beatynge into the ignoraunte peoples eares, this opynion, that is too saye, that these thinges were offered of the Minyster in theyr Masse, for a satysfaccyon of synne, bothe of the quycke and of the deade, as ye shall see in the decretalles of the hyghe Tryny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye
<pb facs="tcp:176398:6"/> and catholyke fayth, <hi>Titu. firmiter cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dimus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reade y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> boke of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> decretals in the title fyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miter credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</note> All men doo alsoo knowe and see what worshyppe hath bene done, and is dayelye done too the mystycall breade of the Lorde: Therefore we do synne no lesse nowe in the Sacramente of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and bloude of Christe, then the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy auntye dyd synne in the Arke of the Lordes couenaunte. Wherefore the righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuouse <note place="margin">Whithe lord dothe at this presente time so horibly pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world.</note> lorde, doth wythoute doubte pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nysshe nowe the worlde, wyth greate &amp; horryble plagues. But nowe that these vngodlye and superstycyons opynyons of the Sacramentes, are oppugned by theym, that haue syncerely preached the iustyfycatyon of faythe, and truth of our Lorde and Sauyoure Iesu Christe, not too thys entente that the Sacramentes shoulde be taken awaye, but that the abuses whyche are aboute theym, super<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stycyouslye and vngodlye taughte, moughte be cleane abolysshed: lo, by and by spryngeth furthe a newe sorte of people, whyche is fallen intoo Scilla <note place="margin">Scilla and C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ribdis are, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Scicilia.</note> couetynge too s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onne Caribdis. For saye they: yf the breade be not made and turned into the verye naturall bodye of
<pb facs="tcp:176398:7"/> Christe, and the wyne intoo hys verye bloude in deede, yea, yf the Sacramente dothe not iustyfye, and brynge grace of it selfe, then it is but bare breade and wyne, nor it skylleth not whether we re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue it or not. Thus these irreuerent per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sons do atrybute to little vnto the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, as the other dydde attrybute too muche. Wherefore the Mynystre shall <note place="margin">What meane the Ministre ought to kepe in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacramēt.</note> wyth a wyse and reuerente symplycytie kepe a meane betwene, and reiectynge all those superstycyons and peruerse o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynyons, shall teache that twoo thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in the Sacramente, muste be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and consydered, that is too saye, the sygne or earthelye elemente, as breade and wyne, wyth the outewarde myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stratyon, and the thynge whyche by the sygne is represented, as the feloweshyp of Christes churche, the body and bloud of oure Lorde, whyche beyng offered for vs on the crosse, haue recouered vntoo mankynde, the loue and fauour of God in so muche that we be nowe made, tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe faythe, and the holye spiryte wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge inwardely, the members and hey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res of Christe, partakers of euerlastynge lyfe, and of all the benefytes of the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="tcp:176398:7"/> begotten sonne of GOD, oure sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge healthe. Wherefore it is not y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noughe <note place="margin">The bare syg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ought not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be set furt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for the Mynyster too preache and set furthe onely the bare sygnes, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glectynge the verye thynge it selfe, as thoughe in the supper of the Lorde, the faythefull shoulde be onelye partakers of breade and wyne, as on the contrarye syde, it is too muche, yf he subuertynge vtterlye the sygnes, dothe teache thee people to venerate and worshyppe the sygnes, for the thynges sygnyfyed by theym: for as the sygnes and tokens oughte circumspectlye too be lymytted, soo we muste haue alwayes a greate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specte too the thynges signyfyed.</p>
            <p>In the matter therefore of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, <note place="margin">The chief and principal thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment must b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> earnestlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hersed and se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the people.</note> the chyefe and pryncypall thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges therof, must be with a due reuerence set furthe and commended vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, that is too saye: the heauenlye and gratuite benetytes of god, wherwith he doth ouerwhelme vs daily &amp; hourely v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing in the meane season thys outwarde signe, as a certaine token and testimony of hys benefycence and lyberalytye to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde vs. For with the sygnes as wyth vysyble wordes he dothe put befoore
<pb facs="tcp:176398:8"/> our eyes his benefites, by theym testify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge and declaryng what he wyll do for vs, if we come vnto him, with adue faith Wherfore it is most necessarye that the <note place="margin">What the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stoures are bound to doo when the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregation go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth aboute to celebrate the maundye.</note> pastores do, with the promise of God, &amp; swete sentences of the gospell, styrre vp the fayth of the congregation, whē they go aboute too celebrate this sacramente, for without fayth, the sacramente dothe not profyte, but hurte, not of it selfe, nor through the fault of the faithful minister but throughe the vnfaythfulnes of hym that receiue it. Secondarelye in this sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> people must be exhorted to thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, to laude and prayse God, for the death of our sauyoure Iesu Christe. For Paule sayth: as often as ye eate of thys <note place="margin">i. Cor. xi, chap</note> breade, and drynke of this cuppe, shewe furthe the lordes deathe tyll he come.</p>
            <p>And for thys cause it was called partely <hi>Eucharistia,</hi> that is too saye: thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng. Moreouer they must seriouslye &amp; <note place="margin">Why the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des supper is called Euch a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ristia.</note> earnestly inculcate and beate into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the people, charitie, loue, studye of concord and true innocencie. Vntoo the which thinges, the sacrament if it be due<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ministred, dothe in a maner of it selfe, moue and rauysshe all men. For who is
<pb facs="tcp:176398:8"/> so dul, and without vnderstanding, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che with this most earnest rehearsall of the benefites of God,, be sydes that, the goodnes of Christe, with a visible appea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunce, signe and token, beynge put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hys eyes, would not be moued too thankefulnes, and mutuall beneficence? Who would not kepe him selfe from the vncleannesse of this worlde, when he se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and heareth that he is made a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of Iesu Christe? Againe▪ who would not louingly embrace his Christian bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, whome he heareth also too be the lymmes of Christ? and to be before god so highly estemed, that he gaue hys one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten sonne, too suffer deathe for <note place="margin">The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt is a test<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial or wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al faith &amp; loue</note> them? And truely the sacramente is a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonyal, wherewyth we do testyfye a mutuall faythe betwene vs, and are in a maner confederate together. We do eat all of one breade, and drynke of one cup The bodye and bloude of Christe dothe fede vs all to euerlastyng lyfe. We are all quyckened wyth one spirite. We are al the members of one bodye. Therfore we ought not to disagre amonge our sel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues, but in Iesu Christ to loue one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to haue al one mynde, and one
<pb facs="tcp:176398:9"/> fayth. Suche thynges dyd the Apostles intreate vpon, when at anye tyme they dyd minister the sacrament of the bodye and bloud of Christ, without any subtyl <note place="margin">Whosoeuer seketh the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyte of Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes churche, must ensue &amp; folow y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of the apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stles.</note> disputatyon or reasonyng: Whose exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, whosoeuer seketh the profyte of the congregation of god, he shall folowe. Al his intent and endeuoure shall be that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> churche may vnderstand the right vse &amp; institution of this sacrament, and flie frō suche curiouse and vaine questions, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly studying to be, throughe faithe, parta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kers of the thynge sygnified in the sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment: That therfore the commune peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whyche is vnlearned and knoweth not the tongues, maye the better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande how they ought to receyue thys sacramente, all superstitious peruerse o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, beyng vtterly extirpated and ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nisshed from emong the faythful subiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of this victoriouse and illustre realme I haue at thys presente tyme compyled and translated out of Latin into English the sayinges or opinions of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> auncyente faythfull fathers vpon the sacrament of the boody and bloude of Christe. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by al men may learne in what reuerence this sacrament, as a seale of the lyuynge
<pb facs="tcp:176398:9"/> god, ought to be had, and how the pure <note place="margin">The pure and sincer antyqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie did alwais kepe it selfe w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in the inclosu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> word of god, in the matter of the sacramentes. The antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes do treade doun the ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunces of Christ y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> theyr vngodly inuē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiōs, &amp; dremes may be set vp.</note> and syncere antiquitie, did kepe it selfe al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wayes within the limites and bondes of the sacred scriptures and worde of God beyng in this poynte farre from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie and vngodlines of our antichristes whych treading vnder fete, the instituty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ordynaunce of our sauyour Iesu Christe, the eternall wisedome of the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly father, did studye for naughte else but to set vp their owne inuentions and dreames: Wherwith the myndes of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny men are so intoxicated and poysoned that it is almoste impossyble to cure and heale them. But I trust that when they haue read this small treatye, whych con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taynethe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> myndes of the olde doctours which almoste all, were by and by after the apostles, beyng faythfullye transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for theyr erudition into their mother tongue, they (I meane them which of ig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noraunce, and not of malyce do erre, wil be the more ready to forsake theyr blynd error, and to folow &amp; embrace the truthe which our most soueraigne lord, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> King &amp; his honorable counsail hath set furthe. And now because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I do know y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> youre mastership hath bene alwaies a louer of
<pb facs="tcp:176398:10"/> the truth, and a hater of superstition, and vngodlines euer, as a valiaūt champione of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the sweard of the spirit, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is gods word, defending the veritye, to y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> vtter ouerthrowing &amp; subuersion of al vngodly errors, which w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the vehemēt &amp; godly spirit of such worshipful men, as your mastership is, being plucked vp by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rootes, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>out any doubte, the kyngdō <note place="margin">Vngodlye er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours beynge plucked vp bi the rootes, Antichristes kyngdom can stand no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> of Antichriste, can not stand no longer, but vanish away as the mist, with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of the bright shining sonne: I haue thought expedient and mete to dedicate this litle work vnto you, in tokē of grati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude &amp; due beneuolence toward your ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stership, beseching moste mekely, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ye of your wont goodnes &amp; facilitie vouchsafe to accept this my rude labour. Herafter wyl I set furth better thinges, in youre masterships name, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the grace of the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing god. Who of his infinite merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes preserue your good mastership, &amp; mi good Lady, your trew louynge spouse &amp; wife, and with his holy spirit so rule and guide your hertes in all your affayres, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> what so euer ye thynke or do, may be to the glorye of god, and saluation of youre soules. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:176398:10"/>
            <head>¶ To the christen reader, Ihon Veron wissheth health of bodye and soule, from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father, throughe oure lord Iesu Chryste.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I procede anye farther, good christē rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> shalt vnderstand y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy fathers of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient &amp; primitiue church do in manye places of their writinges, cal this Sacramente the bodye and bloude of oure Lorde and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyoure Iesu Christe. Whyche thynge verelye they dyd, notte because that they had anye suche carnall opynyon in them as is nowe amonge a greate sorte of learned menne, and greate Clarkes, but because that they beynge thorowelye exercysed in the holye and sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Byble, had learned, that the Sacramentes of holye thynges, dyd take the names of the verye selfe same thynges, whereof they are Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. <note place="margin">Augu. ad Bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>facium. Gene, xvii. cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Fyrst, they had read y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacrament of cir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cūsitiō, was called, <hi>Pactū siue foedus domini</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:176398:11"/> in the couenaunt of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord. Which thing notw<seg rend="sup">t</seg>standing was not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very couenant in dede: but a signe, tokē, sacrament &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morial of the couenaunt y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> was betwene god and Abraham. Again, how y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Iacob did cal the altare that he had builded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lord, <hi>Deum Bethel,</hi> the God of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel, and the place where he wrastled w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <note place="margin">Genes. xxviii. Chapi. &amp; xxxii. Chapiter.</note> the aungel. <hi>Phuiel seu Phaniel,</hi> the face of god. Now (as I suppose) noo man wyll iudge or thinke, except he were without al humain vnderstanding, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same heap of stones which Iacob had gathered to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether, was y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> God of Bethel, or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> place where he wrastled w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the angel, was the face of god in verye dede. But whye are they so called thē? Verelye y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the name it<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>self might put men in remembraune of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> by thē was signified &amp; betokened Euen as afterwardes, when y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> childrē of Israel wer deliuered out of Egipt, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pas<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cal lambe (which was a sacrament most reuerently kept alwaies emong y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Iues) was called <hi>Pesac, id est transitus domini,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lordes passeouer, that they hearinge this <note place="margin">Exod. xi. Cha</note> word, passeouer might immediatly cal in to their remembraunce, the innumerable benefites of their mighty &amp; omnipotent
<pb facs="tcp:176398:11"/> sauiour. Which passing by throughe the land of their enemies, did slaye al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> firste born of Egipt, &amp; so with a mighty &amp; stret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched furth arme, did bring them safe tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> red sea, from al misery, wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; thraldom, into a land that floweth with milke &amp; hony, And verelye when y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lambe was once selected, chosen &amp; taken out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flocke, and applied to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy vse that god, by hys seruaunte Moises, had before theyr deliueraunce out of Egipte instituted and ordeined, it was noo more called a lambe, but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> passeouer of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lorde Which phrase &amp; maner of speaking, all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> auncyente fathers and prophetes of the old Testament, did vse alwayes in theyr sermons and writynges. And our Lorde Iesus Christ, the euerlastinge wisedome of god the father, did confirme the same, when he did institute and ordaine the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his death and passyon vntoo vs, callynge the sacramente of his bodye &amp; bloud, by the very name of those most holy and sacred thinges, which by it are signified. That when in the celebratyon of the holy misteries, we doo heare these wordes. <hi>This is my bodye, and this is my bloud,</hi> Marke well good reader the ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>logie
<pb facs="tcp:176398:12"/> of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> old &amp; new sacraments, for he y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saith of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lamb, <hi>This is the passeouer of the lord,</hi> which this night shal passe by, doth say also of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bread, <hi>This is my body,</hi> which shal be deliuered for you, we by &amp; by put before our eies that most precious body, which so pitiously on y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> crosse, was brokē for vs, &amp; also his most holy &amp; sacred blud which w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the handes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vngodlye, was<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shed for our sinnes, wherfore (as I haue said before of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lambe) when the bread &amp; wine, is by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> true and faithful ministers preaching &amp; anunciatyng y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lordes death and passion vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> christen people, appli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed vnto y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thing which our sauioure hath ordeyned, it is no lenger called bread and wine (though in some places of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res we fynd that both Luke &amp; Paule do cal it bread, &amp; the cup) but the bodye and bloud of our lord: and for this cause doth S. Paul say: he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> eateth of thys bread, &amp; drinketh of this cup vnworthely, shal be gylty of the body &amp; bloud of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord. As if he should say: he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> regardeth not the pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pose, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which, Christ did institute this sacramente, which commeth not vnto it with a spiritual hunger, to eate throughe faith his very body, and with a spirituall
<pb facs="tcp:176398:12"/> thirst, to drinke through faith, hys verye bloud which by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> breade &amp; wyne, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented, he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> doth not put away al ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lice, rancor, &amp; vncharitablenes from hys hert, &amp; study to vnitie, loue, and concorde which by this mistical breade is betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto vs, he that doth not come vnto this feast &amp; banket with a mery hert, ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing god herty thankes, for our delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce out of synne, he which dothe not much more eat y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> death of the lord in his hert, then y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bread w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his mouth, is giltye of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body and bloud of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lorde and so he doth eate and drinke his owne dampna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, because he maketh no difference of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lordes body, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say, putteth no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwene this eatinge &amp; other ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which serueth onelye for the bealy, where as this eating was instituted &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dained to serue the soule &amp; inward man. And therfore he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> abuseth it to y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> flesh, ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth &amp; drinketh his owne dampnatyon, and commeth vnworthely to the banket where the sacramente of Christes bodye, is eaten, yea, where y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord is ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten, not carnally with the rethe and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but spiritually with hearte, faith, and spirite. These phrases, I saye, and maner
<pb facs="tcp:176398:13"/> of speaking do the holye fathers vse ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, when they do intreat vpō this sacrament, which at the first sight, maye seme to avow the bodely and carnal pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sence of Christ, in the sacrament &amp; holye supper, but if they be wel pondered, mē shal sone perceiue &amp; vnderstand howthei ought to be taken. For it is the custome &amp; vse of the auncient doctors, when they speake of the sacrament &amp; outwarde ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to apply vnto the sacrament &amp; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eating, the frutes, profites, &amp; condi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions of the spiritual &amp; inward eatinge, &amp; also of the thing it self, which by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is signified. Because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in a faithful man, thei are so ioyntly ioined, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the one is neuer without y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> other: As by example we say y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> god died &amp; suffered for vs, &amp; yet the godhead of Christ, by the which part onely he is called god, dyd neuer suffer. But because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the godhead is so anexed w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the manhod, that they both make but one person, it is said y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> god suffered for vs Which thing, if it be wel loked vpon, cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sidered &amp; weied, shal be fonde to be an ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>used &amp; an vnpropre speache, &amp; yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles, it may wel be vsed, if men vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand what is meant therby. A very like
<pb facs="tcp:176398:13"/> example haue we in the thirde of Ihon. Where Christ saith, no man ascendeth in to heauen, but he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> descendeth frō heauē the son of man which is in heauē. Mark &amp; vnderstand: this scripture doth say &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stifye, that the sonne of manne was then in heauen, when he spake these wordes, vnto Nicodemus, here vpon earth, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thing al wisemen do graunt y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it was spoken. <hi>propter vnitatem personae,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is too say, for the vnitie of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> persō. For though his godhead were in euery place at that time, yet was not his manhod, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che he is called y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sonne of man, in heauē at y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> time: And yet Christ said y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it was in heauē for his vnitie of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> persō. For hys godhead was in heauen, &amp; because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the godhead &amp; manhode do make one persō therfore y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> was adscrybed vnto the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode, which was verified vpō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> godhed But now by the sacrament of baptisme we wil make this our matter more mani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fest &amp; plain. In this sacrament (I meane baptisme) the inward working of the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly gost, is euer in the faithful persons, an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nexed vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> outward ceremonies: Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore sometime the fruicte of the inwarde baptisme is adscribed vnto the outward
<pb facs="tcp:176398:14"/> worke, &amp; so y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scripture vseth to speake of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> outward baptisme, as though it wer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> inward, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy gost. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore S. Paul doth saye, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we are buryed w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Christ, through baptisme, &amp; yet y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward baptisme did but signify this bury<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>al. And again Paul doth say, as mani as are baptised, haue put Christ vpon them And yet in dede our outward baptisme, doth but signify y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we haue put Christ vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on vs: But by y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> inward baptisme, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the water of life, &amp; the spirit of god we haue in dede put hym on, we liue in him, &amp; he in vs. Which thyng truely can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be verified of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> outward baptisme in thē, which do not receiue it w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> faith. For vnto them it is but a bare sygne, wherof they get no profit, but damnatiō. And ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rely so it is of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacrament &amp; holy supper of our lord. For in it y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scripture &amp; all the auncient doctors do adscribe vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worke &amp; ceremony, which is onely true in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> inward veritie. For they onely eat y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> flesh of the lord, &amp; drinke his bloud not carnally w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> teth &amp; mouth: but spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> faith. which dwel in Christ, and in whō Christ dwelleth: The veritie it selfe saying: he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> eateth my flesshe, &amp; drinketh
<pb facs="tcp:176398:14"/> my bloud, dwelleth in mee, &amp; I in hym. Thus ye may se, how y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy fathers of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> auncient &amp; old church ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>standed in this matter of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacramente &amp; supper of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord. Which thei do cal <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ristiam,</hi> a thankes geuing, because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> by it the faithful &amp; godly, are moued too geue high &amp; immortal thankes vnto god, their heauenly father, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> death of his onely begotten son, Iesu Christ. Sometime <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naxin,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say, a charitable cōming to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faithful, vnto thys holy maū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy &amp; feast of euerlastinge life. And other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles a sacrifice, because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> as Chrisostō saith, it is a memorial of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> omnisufficient sacrifice, ones for euer offered in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> altare of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> crosse. Yea y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very missaries (y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> truth compelling thē to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same) do cal it y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stery of faith, &amp; the sacrifice of laude and praise. These thinges therfore, good chry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sten reader, y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> shalte depely prynte in thy mind &amp; memory, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thou maieste herafter w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>stand y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> enemies of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> truth, which eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry where do bost &amp; crake, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the holy doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors do stand &amp; make for thē, where as yf they be wel vnderstanded, they do all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainste them. For that whiche they doo brynge out of Cipryan and Ambrose, all godly learned men do agre, that they
<pb facs="tcp:176398:15"/> they were not Cipryans nor Ambroses workes, but workes falsly adscribed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, by such false antichristes as intē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded to bryng in this erromus, doctryne into the churche of Christe. Therfore let no such sayinges moue the, but sticking to the spirit which quickeneth, studye w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> al thy endeuour, to be made one body w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> our head, Iesu Christ, which in his glori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied body, sitteth on y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> right hand of god the father, tyl his enemyes be made hys fote stole. As for my parte, I wil daily &amp; hourely beseche that almighty lorde, the father of al mercy and comfort, whyche did send his onely begotten sonne, Iesu Christ into this world, with al plenitude of heauenly doctrine, bidding vs to hear him, as his welbeloued son, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe with his spirit, to kindle▪ rauishe and inflame our heartes, to the feruente loue of his doctrine onely, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> so with one faith and one consent, reiecting the dreames &amp; doctrines of men, we maye fede oure soules with the heauenly fode of the Scriptures and worde of god. To whō be prayse glory and honour for euer. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:176398:15"/>
            <head>¶ The godly sayinges of the old faithful fathers, vpon the sacrament of the body and bloude of Christ.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Augustyne, in a Sermon made to the chyldren and infances, touchynge the sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramente.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat, which ye se in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> altare of god, ye dyd se it also, the nyghte before: But what it was, what it doth mean, and of how great a thyng it doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne a sacrament, ye haue not yet herd. That therfore which <note place="margin">Thys Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of faythe.</note> ye do se, is bread, and that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is set before your eyes, is a cup: But touching that wherin your faith desireth to be instruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted: The breade is the bodye of Christ, and the cup his bloude. Truely, this is brieflye spoken, and which paraduēture might
<pb facs="tcp:176398:16"/> suffise the faith: But faith requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth further instructyon. For y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prophet sayth: except ye beleue ye shal not vnderstand. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Esaie. vi. cha.</note> ye may say vnto me nowe: Thou hast bidden vs to beleue, expound, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we may vnderstand For suche an imaginatyon may rise in any mannes mynde: We know y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> our lord Iesus Christe dyd take hys fleshe of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Virgin Mary. He beyng an infant, did <note place="margin">The carnall natiuite of Chryst is here shewed &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clared.</note> sucke, was broughte vp, dydde growe, and came to mans state He did suffer persecution of the Iues, he was hanged vpon the crosse, &amp; there he dyed. He was buryed, and the thyrde daye he rose again. On what dai it plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed him, he did ascende into hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen. Thether dyd he carye vp hys body, from whence he shall come, too iudge the quycke and
<pb facs="tcp:176398:16"/> the deade. There he is now sit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge on the ryght hand of the father. Howe can, ergo, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> bread be hys bodye, and the cuppe, or that whiche is in the cup, be his bloude? These thinges brethrē are therfore called sacraments because that in them, one thing is sene, and an other thinge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanded. That which is sene hath a vysyble apperaunce or forme, but that whych is vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>standed, hath a spiritual vtilitie &amp; profit. If thou wilt thē vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stand y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of Christ hear the <note place="margin">i. Cor. xii cha. We our selfs are the bodye of Christe.</note> apostle, saying vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faithfull: Ye are y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of Christ, &amp; hys membres. Therfore, if ye are y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of Christ, &amp; hys members your misteri is put vpon y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> table of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord, and ye receiue also the mystery of the Lorde. To that which ye are, ye answere: Amen,
<pb facs="tcp:176398:17"/> and in aunswearynge, yee sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe vnto it. Thou dost heare therfore the body of Christ, and thou answerest. Amen. Be thou a membre of the body of Christ that thy Amen, may be true. Why is it therfore ministred in breade? Let vs here brynge no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thyng of our owne, but heare y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> apostle him self, which when he speaketh of the sacrament, saith Thoughe we be manye, we are one breade, and one bodye. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand <note place="margin">i. Corinthi. x.</note> and reioyce: Therein is vnytye, godlines, truth, and charitie. Though we be manye (saith he) we are one bread and one bodi: Remembre y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> bread is not made of one corn: but of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny. <note place="margin">How y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bread is made.</note> When ye were exorcised, ye were in a maner ground, when ye were baptized, ye were as a man should say, knode together
<pb facs="tcp:176398:17"/> When ye did receyue the sancti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fication <note place="margin">A mete or apt similitude and comparisō be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that are brought vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faithe, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bread whych is made of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye cornes.</note> of the holy gost, ye wer in a maner, baken. Be ye y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ye se, and receiue y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which ye are. The apostle did say this of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bread. Now what we oughte to vnderstand of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cup, though not one word therof is spoken, yet it declareth and sheweth it<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfe sufficyently. For euen as, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> there may be one visyble forme of breade, manye Cornes are knode together in one (asthogh that were done, which the holy scripture doth saye of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, they had al one mynd, &amp; one <note place="margin">Actes .iiii. cha</note> hert to god) so remembre ye bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thrē, wherof wine is made. Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">How wine is made.</note> grapes do hang vpō a cluster but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> licour of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> grapes, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded together in one. Soo our lord Iesus christ signifiyng vs, &amp; willing vs to pertayn vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:176398:18"/> him, did consecrate vpon his bourd, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mystery of our peace &amp; <note place="margin">The sacramēt is a mistery of vnitie &amp; loue.</note> vnitie. He y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> receiueth the miste<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of vnytye, and doth not kepe the knot &amp; bonde of peace, doth not receiue the mistery for him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfe: but a witnes agaynst hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfe: Ne no man ought to dout but that euery one of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, is made partaker of the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy and bloude of Christe, when in baptisme, he is made a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Christe, and that no man <note place="margin">The yong ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bes being bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyzed▪ are also partakers of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord thoughe they do die afore y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thei do receue the sacramēt.</note> is put or enstraunged from the partakynge of this breade, and of this cup, if he be in the vnitye of the body of Christ, though he doth depart out of this worlde, afore that he doth eate of thys bread, and drinke of this cuppe. For he can in no wise be depry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> partaking &amp; benefyt of this sacramente, when he hath
.
<pb facs="tcp:176398:18"/> foūd &amp; gotten y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> self same thing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the sacrament doth signifye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Our of a sermon of S. Augustine, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng the sacramentes of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. made vpon the seconde ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye daye of Easter.</head>
               <p>¶ Because that Christ hath suf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fered for vs, he hath betakē vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs in this sacramēt, his body &amp; his bloud, whych he hath also made, euē vs our selfes. For we are also made his body, and by hys mercye wee are euen the same thynge that we receyue. Remembre that ones ye were not, and ye haue bene created. Ye were brought into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> floore <note place="margin">How we are made y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lords breade,</note> of the lorde, wyth the laboures of the Oxen, that is too saye, of them that did preache y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gospel, yee were thresshed. Whyles youre Cathechysme lasted, ye <note place="margin">Cathechisme is as much to saie institutiō and teaching<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> were kept in the barne. Ye did giue your names, &amp; began to be
<pb facs="tcp:176398:19"/> ground, with fastinges &amp; exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cysmes. Afterwardes, ye came to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> water, &amp; beyng knode, wer made the bread of the lord. Lo what ye haue receyued. There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore as that whiche ye see, was made one, so be ye all one in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge etche other, in kepyng e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge <note place="margin">Let vs be one in loue as the bread is made one of many cornes.</note> you, one fayth and hope and one indissoluble loue. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques when they do receiue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, they do receiue a witnes against thē selues, because that they seke a diuisiō, wheras this breade doth betoken an vnitie. So y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wine was in manye clus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp; now is one. It is one in the swetenes of the cup, after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pressing of the wine presse. And ye after your fasting and labou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, after your humylite &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition of hearte, are in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> name of Christ, as if a man should say
<pb facs="tcp:176398:19"/> come to the Chalice of Christe. There are ye vpō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> table, there are ye in the chalice. And toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with vs ye are. For we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue it together, we drynke it together, because we liue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If any man do eat of this bread, he shal liue for euer, &amp; the bread which I shall geue, is my flesh, which I shal geue for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> life <note place="margin">Flesh is takē in thys place, I meane the flesh whyche doth not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, for a carnall man y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> vnderstādeth al thinges af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flesshe, &amp; as they are spoken. Ye shall haue these wordes vpon Ihon, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> xxxv. treatye.</note> of the world. When should flesh vnderstand howe he dydde call bread flesh? That is called flesh y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> flesh doth not vnderstande, &amp; much more flesshe doth not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand it, because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it is called flesh, for they were astonied atit &amp; murmured emong thē selues thinking y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it could not be done. My flesh (saith he) for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> life of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world. The faithfull do vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the body of Christ, if they thē selues do not despise to be y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176398:20"/> body of Christe, let thē be made y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of Christ, if they wil liue with the spirit of Christ. Onely the bodye of Christe, doth lyue with the spirite of Christ. Take ye hede my brethren, what I <note place="margin">We can not liue w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Christ ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept we be in the body of Christe.</note> haue sayde. Thou arte a man and haste bothe a spiryte and a bodye. I vnderstand by the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, that which is called y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> soule wherewyth thou beinge a man arte compacte and made. For thou doest consyste of soule and <note place="margin">The spirit is takē in a man for the soule,</note> bodye. Thou haste therfore an inuysyble spiryte, and a vysyble bodye, Tell me whether of thē hath his lyfe of the other. Hath thy spiryte hys lyfe of thy body or thy bodye of thy spiryte? All menne lyuynge wyll saye: wee haue lyfe of the spirit. And sure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, he that can not answere this I can not tel whether he liueth
<pb facs="tcp:176398:20"/> or not. What do aunsweare all men lyuynge? Truely we haue lyfe of oure spirite. Wylte thou thē liue with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> spiryt of Christ? Be thou in the body of Christe. Doth my body liue with thi spi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit? My bodye lyueth with my spirit, and thy body liueth with thy spirit. The body of Christe, can not liue: but w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his spirit of <note place="margin">He y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is not in the bodye of Christe dothe not liue in the spirite of Christ, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore he is not his, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of the sacramente profiteth him nothing. i. Corin. x. How sinners may be made thee bodye of Christe.</note> Christ. Therfore y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Apostle S. Paule, expounding this breade saith: Though we be many, we are one breade and one bodye. O sacramente of godlines. Oh signe of vnitie. O bonde of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and loue. He that will liue hath wherewyth he may lyue, let hym come nere, let hym be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, let him be incorrupted and quyckened. Lette hym notte goo from the ioynture and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>page of the members. Let him
<pb facs="tcp:176398:21"/> not be a rotten limme, which de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>serueth to be cut of, let hym not be croked, wherof he may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed let him be fayre, plain &amp; whole, let him cleaue to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye. Let hym lyue to God, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row god. Let hym now labour in earthe, that afterwardes he maye lyue in heauen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ In the same Sermon.</head>
            <p>HE wyll that this meate and drinke, shuld be vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derstand <note place="margin">The misticall bread &amp; drink is y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> feloshyp of the faythe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful.</note> to be y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and societie of his body and of his membres, which is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly congregation in his predesti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nate and called, in his iustyfyed and glorified sainctes and faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful. Of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which the fyrst is done <note place="margin">The .iiii. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gres of mans saluation.</note> alredy, that is to say, predestina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion. The second and thyrd are done, be now a doing, and heraf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter shall be done, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say, call<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="tcp:176398:21"/> and iustificatiō. The fourth is now in hope, &amp; herafter shall be fulfilled in dede, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to saye, glorifyinge. The sacramente of this thing, is prepared in some place daily, and in some place, at certain appointed times, as vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on the sonday. And it is recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <note place="margin">The thynge signifyed bye the sacamente is vnto all mē that are parta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kers thereof vnto lyfe and to no man vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to destructiō.</note> at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> table of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lorde, of some vnto life, and of some vntoo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction. But the thing it selfe, whose sacrament this is, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of all men vnto lyfe, and of no man vnto destructiō, who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>soeuer is partaker of it. For my flesh (saith he) is meate in dede, and my bloud is drinke in dede For sithe that men do onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire and couet, with meate and drinke, to put awaye their hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thyrst: This meate one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly (whiche maketh them, of whō it is taken, immortal and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptyble)
<pb facs="tcp:176398:22"/> and thys drynke can do it, that is to saye, the felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyp of the saynctes, where full &amp; perfite peace and vnytye shal be. Wherefore, (as holy men of god, haue perceyued before vs) <note place="margin">This meate is the feloship of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sainctes.</note> oure Lorde Iesus Christe, dyd betake hys body and his bloud in those thinges whiche can be <note place="margin">Why Christe did betake vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs his bodi and bloude in breade &amp; wine</note> redacted into some one thynge of manye. For the one is made of many cornes. one: and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth runne together into one, oute of manye grapes. He <note place="margin">Ihon .vi. cha.</note> that eateth my flesshe, and drin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth my bloud, dwelleth in me, and I in hym. This is therfore <note place="margin">An vngodlye person eateth nothing but thesigne though he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue neuer soo often the sacramente.</note> to eate that meat, and to drinke that drinke, to dwel in Christ, &amp; to haue Christ dwelling in him And by thys, he that dwelleth not in Christe, and in whome Christ doth not dwel, doth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:176398:22"/> eat his flesh, nor drinke his bloud, though he doth eate and drinke the sacrament of so high a thing, to his own dampnatiō.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Augustin .i. quinquage. Psalme .xxxix.</head>
               <p>¶ That first sacrifice being abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lisshed, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> brent offerings of ram<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes, <note place="margin">Al the sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the old law were but fygures &amp; sha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dous of that only sacrifice ones offred in the crosse, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che sacryfyce endurethe for euer: nor we nede no more sacrifices but of praise and thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge. &amp;c. The promys ones made is now perfour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med.</note> gotes, calues, &amp; other bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stes, beinge taken awaye: The lord would none of them. Why would he none of thē, sith y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first he wold haue thē? Because that they al were words of pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mise, and the words of promise, when that is come, whych they do promise, be not vsed or spokē A man is stil called a promyser, till he doth geue. When he hath geuen, he dothe chaunge hys wordes. He doth not saye styll: I wyll geue that whyche I haue promysed: but I haue gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and soo he hath chaunged
<pb facs="tcp:176398:23"/> hys words. Why did this word please hym fyrst, and why hath he chaunged it? Because it was a worde of that tyme, &amp; for that time it dyd please. Whyles the promise lasted, it was spoken &amp; vsed. But when that is geuen, which was promysed, the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of promise are taken away and the wordes of performaūce geuen. Therfore those sacrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as wordes of promise, are taken away. What word of per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formaunce is geuē vs? That bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy which ye do knowe, whyche wold god ye knew not to your owne dampnation. Thou wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest <note place="margin">Psalme .xxxix.</note> no sacrifice (saith he) nor ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latyō. What then? Are we now left without a sacrifice? God for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bid. For saith he, thou hast made me a body. Therfore thou wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest none of them, because thou
<pb facs="tcp:176398:23"/> mighteste performe thys. The performynge of the promyses hath taken away the wordes of promyse. Thys was promysed wyth certayne signes. The syg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes be taken away, &amp; the truth which was promised, is alreadi geuen and exhibited. We are in this body, we are partakers of this body. We knowe what we do receiue. And ye that knowe <note place="margin">i. Cor. xi. cha.</note> not, learne: and when yee haue learned, beware that ye receiue it not to your own dampnatiō. For he that eateth &amp; drynketh vnworthely, doth eate &amp; drinke hys owne dampnation. A body is made vntoo vs, let vs bee made perfite in the bodie.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ August. in the .xxvi. treatie vpō Ihon.</head>
            <p>HOw manye do receiue of the altare, and dye? yea, by receauing do in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curre
<pb facs="tcp:176398:24"/> death? Wherfore the apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stle <note place="margin">i. Cor. xi. cha</note> saith: He doth eate &amp; drinke hys owne dampnation. For the morsel of the lorde, was poyson vnto Iudas, and yet he did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it, &amp; when he had receiued it, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> enemy did entre into hym. Not because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he had receiued any euil thyng: but because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he being wicked, did receiue it wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kedly. Marke ye therefore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. Eate ye thys spirytuall bread, spiritually. Bring innocē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie of life, to the altare. Though your sinnes be daily &amp; quotidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, <note place="margin">Let noo man come to the lordes table excepte he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente truely.</note> let not them be deadly. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ye come too y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> altare, take ye hede what ye saye. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue vs oure trespaces, as we forgiue them y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> trespace against vs. Dost thou forgiue? it shalbe <note place="margin">The lorde can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of any man.</note> forgiuen vnto the. Come bolde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye, it is bread, and not poyson.
<pb facs="tcp:176398:24"/> But se whether thou doste for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue or not, for if y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> doest not for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giue, thou makest a lye, and liest vnto him, whom thou canst not beguyle. Thou mayest make a lie vnto god, but thou canst not <note place="margin">God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the tames and heartes of men.</note> deceiue god. He knoweth what thou doest: He seeth the within, he examyneth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>in, he loketh vpō the wythin, he iudgeth the w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>in, he doth either condempne or rewarde y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> within. Therfore the fathers of them, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to saye wycked fathers of the wycked, murmuring fathers, of murmu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rers. (For we do not reade, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <note place="margin">Murmuring is one of thee gretest sinnes against god.</note> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord was so greuously of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> any thing, as w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring against God) the lorde willing to shew that they were the chyldren of suche, beganne w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> them, after this maner: what doo ye murmure emonge you, O ye murmurers, chyldren of
<pb facs="tcp:176398:25"/> murmurers. Your fathers did eate Manna in the deserte, and are dead. Not because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na was euyll, but because that they dyd eat it wickedly. This is the breade whyche commeth doun from heauen. Manna did <note place="margin">Manna was a figure of Christ, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly breade The sacramē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> old &amp; new testamēt did differre in signes, but in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thing which is signyfyed they be al one i. Corinthi. x.</note> signify this bread, the altar did signify this breade. They were sacramentes, and dyd dyffer in signes, but in the thing, whyche is signified, they be al one. Hear the Apostle: For I wyl not that ye be ignoraunt, brethren, that our fathers were all vnder the cloude, and went al thorow the Sea, and were all baptized by Moses, in the cloud, and in the sea, and al dyd eate one spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al meate: Euen the same spiry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall meate, albeit, an other bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely meat. For they didde eate Manna, &amp; we do eate an other
<pb facs="tcp:176398:25"/> thing. But they did eate y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same spiritual, that we do: but our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, vnto whome we are like, and not theirs. Moreouer, he saith, &amp; they did drynke all one spiritual drinke, thei dranke one thinge, and we an other. But y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> was in the outward apperaūce which neuertheles did signifye the selfe same thing spiritually. And how did thei drinke al one drinke? sayth the apostle: They did drinke of the spiritual rocke that foloweth thē, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rocke was Christe. Thereof haue we bread, thereof haue we drinke. The rocke was Christ, in signe and fygure, now is y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> very true Christ in the word, &amp; in the flesh And how did they drinke? The rocke was twise smitten w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the <note place="margin">Exod. vii. cha.</note> rod. The twise smiting, did syg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifie the two peces of the crosse
<pb facs="tcp:176398:26"/> This is therefore the breade y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> commeth downe from heauen, wherof yf any man dothe eate, <note place="margin">It must be a spiritual ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge.</note> he shal not dye: But he that per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayneth to the vertue of the sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramente, not hee that partay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the visyble sygne. He y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eateth inwardly, and not oute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly. He that eateth w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his hert, not he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> presseth with hys tethe. Manna came downe frō heauen: But Manna was a shadowe, and thys is a veritie.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Augustine, vpon the wordes of Christe, the .lxiii. Sermon.</head>
               <p>¶ Moste dere beloued, we be <note place="margin">i. Ihon. iii cha</note> the chyldren of God, by grace, by faythe, by the Sacramente, by the bloude of Christe, by the redemptyon of oure sauyoure, we are the chyldren of GOD: It didde not yet appeare what
<pb facs="tcp:176398:26"/> we shall be. We know that whē he doth appere, we shall be lyke vnto him. For we shall se hym, euē as he is. Lo, to what thing <note place="margin">Spirituall meate is not minysshed.</note> we are nourisshed, to receiue &amp; eate, and yet notwithstandyng that thing which is eatē, is not minisshed, wheras he that doth eate is quickened. Other meat though in eating it quickeneth the bodye, yet when it is eaten it is mynysshed: But when we shall begynne too eate ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousenes, too eate wysedome, to eate that immortal meate, both we shall be quyckened, and the meate not mynysshed. Yf some excellente meate were praysed vntoo thee, whyche thou shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest <note place="margin">Agaynst thys holy supper we muste pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our sou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les &amp; not our bealyes.</note> eate at thy diner, thou wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deste prepare thy bealye, nowe God is praysed vntoo the, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy soule.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:176398:27"/>
               <head>¶ Augustine, vpon the wordes of the apostle, the second Sermon.</head>
               <p>¶ When he therfore, betakyng vnto vs suche meate and suche <note place="margin">Ihon .vi. Cha</note> drynke, did saye, excepte ye eate my flesh, and drinke my bloude, ye shal not haue life in you. Did any other thē life it selfe, speake these wordes of lyfe? But it wil be death vntoo that man, &amp; not life, that thinketh life to be a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. His disciples wer offended, not all, but many: saying to thē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selues. This is an harde saying who can heare it? What mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thys? Doth thys offende you? Do ye thinke that I wyll make partes of this body, &amp; cut in sunder my membres, &amp; geue them vnto you? What, yf ye do <note place="margin">Christ coulde not be consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</note> se the sonne of man, ascendynge where he was before? Truely, he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ascendeth wholl, can not be consumed. Therefore he dydde
<pb facs="tcp:176398:27"/> both geue vnto vs an wholsom refection of his body, and of his bloud, and also did brieflie assoil that hard question of his whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Let them eate thē, that do <note place="margin">What is too eate y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall meate &amp; drinke y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall drinke.</note> eate, and drinke that do drinke let them hunger and thirst. Let them eate lyfe, let them drynke lyfe. That eating is a refection in dede, and yet thou art so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectyoned, that thou canste not lacke, wherof to be refectioned. What other thing here, is it to drinke, but too lyue? Eate lyfe, drinke lyfe, and thou shalt haue life, &amp; yet the life is whole. But that wyl be, that is too saye, the body and bloud of Christe, shall be lyfe vnto euery man, yf that which is taken visibly in the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, be eaten and dronken spiritually in the veritie it selfe. For we haue herd the lord say:
<pb facs="tcp:176398:28"/> It is the spirit that quickeneth the flesshe profiteth nothinge. <note place="margin">Ihon .vi. cha</note> The wordes that I haue spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto you, are spirite &amp; lyfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Augustine, in the .xxi. boke of the citie of God, and .xv. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>¶ This is the bread that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth downe from heauen, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man eateth of it, he shall not <note place="margin">Ihon .vi. cha</note> die. I am the liuely breade that commeth downe from heauen, if anye manne doth eate of this bread, he shal liue for euer. Not without a cause, it is asked how it ought to be taken. And from them truely, vnto whom we an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swere nowe, they vnto whome we shall aunswere hereafter do take away thys vnderstanding These be they y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> promyse thys delyueraunce, not to all theym that haue receiued the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of baptisme, &amp; of the body
<pb facs="tcp:176398:28"/> of Christ: but too the catholyke onely, though they liue wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. For (say thei) they do not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly eat in the sacrament or sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentally: but in very dede, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy of Christ, and y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> because that they are in his body, of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which body, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> apostle saithe: Thoughe <note place="margin">i. Corin. x</note> we be many, we be one bread, &amp; one body. Ergo, he which is in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vnitie of his body (y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> knot of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> membres of Christ) <note place="margin">Who be the trewe eaters.</note> of the which body y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faithfull in their communion, are wonte to receiue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacrament, we oughte (I say) verely to esteme, that he doth eat y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of Christe, and drinke his blud. And by this, he ritikes &amp; scismatikes being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided frō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vnitie of thys body, maye receiue y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> selfe same sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt: but not holsom &amp; profitable vnto them, but rather noisom &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:176398:29"/> hurtful, Whereby they shal the sooner be condemned, or the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be delyuered. For they are not in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> knot &amp; bonde of peace, <note place="margin">Peace &amp; vnite is expressed in the sacramēt.</note> which is expressed in this sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ In that same Chapiter.</head>
               <p>¶ He that eateth my flesh, and drinketh my bloud, dwelleth in mee, and I in him. He sheweth what is to eat, not sacramental lye, but in very dede the bodye of Christ, &amp; to drinke his bloud. For that is to dwell in Christe, that Christ may dwel in vs, for <note place="margin">Vnitie &amp; loue onely dothe fede vpon the body &amp; bloud of Christe.</note> he dyd speake thys thynge, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he should say: he whych dwelleth not in me, and in whō I do not dwell, let him not saye or thinke that he eateth my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or drinketh my bloud. They do not therfore dwell in Christ which are not his lymmes, but
<pb facs="tcp:176398:29"/> they are not his limmes, which make theym selues y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> membres of an harlotte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Augustine vpon Ihon .xxvi. treatye.</head>
               <p>¶ He that eateth my flesh, and drinketh my bloud, dwelleth in me, and I in him. This is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">By these wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ye may se that the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very body of Christ else the wicked which dwelleth not in Christ shuld eate his fleshe</note> to eate that meate, and too drinke that drinke, too dwell in Christ, and to haue Christ dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling in him. And by this, he that dwelleth not in Christe, and in whom Christ doth not dwel, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out doubt, he doth neither eate the flesh of Christe spirituallye, nor drinke his bloud, though he doth carnally and visibly presse with hys teth, the sacrament of the body and bloud of Christe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Augustine the .xxvii. treatie, and .vi. Chapiter of Ihon.</head>
               <p>¶ And he did expound the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the distributyon of thys
<pb facs="tcp:176398:30"/> hys gift, how he shuld giue hys flesh to eate, saying: He that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth my flesshe. &amp;c. This is a to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken, that he hath eatē &amp; dronke <note place="margin">The trewe waie to eate the bodye of Christe</note> yf he dwel, and be dwelled with all, yf he dothe inhabite, and be inhabyted, yf he doth stycke fast vntoo, and be not forsaken. He hath therefore taught and war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned vs, wyth these mistical wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, that we shoulde be in hys body and members, vnder him as oure heade, eatyng his flesh and not forsakynge the vnytye of hys bodye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>If ye se the son of man ascending where he was before.</head>
               <p>¶ What is thys? w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> these wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des he dothe assoile thē, whō he knewe: Wyth these wordes he doth declare &amp; shew wherefore they wer offended, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> these wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des truly, if they mought haue
<pb facs="tcp:176398:30"/> vnderstāded. For they thought that he shuld erogate and part his body emonge them: But he <note place="margin">Why the ieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es were offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> sayth, that he shall ascende into heauen whole: When ye shall se the sonne of manne ascendynge where he was before: Then tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ye shal se that he doth not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stribute his body, after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that ye thynke. Verelye ye <note place="margin">The grace of god can not be consumed</note> shall vnderstand that his grace is not consumed wyth tethe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Augustine .ii. quinquage. rcviii. Psalme</head>
               <p>¶ When the Lorde did betake thys vnto vs, he had spoken of hys flesshe, and sayde: Excepte a manne dothe eate my flesshe, he shall not haue in hym, lyfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlastynge. And he sayde, the wordes that I haue spoken vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">The natura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> body of chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is not eaten nor his blou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dronken.</note> you, are spiryte and life. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der stande ye spiritually, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I haue spokē vnto you. Ye
<pb facs="tcp:176398:31"/> shall not eate this body whiche ye se, nor drinke the bloud whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they shal shede, that shal cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifie me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Augustine in the third boke of the Chrysty an doctryne.</head>
               <p>¶ Excepte ye eate the flesshe of the sonne of man, &amp; drynke hys bloude, ye shall not haue lyfe in you. He semeth to commaunde <note place="margin">To eate, is to be partaker of the passion of Christe.</note> a foule and wicked thing. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it is a figure, cōmaundinge vs to be partakers of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lordes passion, and to printe in our me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mory swetly, that his flesh was crucifyed and wounded for vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ In the decrees of penaunce, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> seconde distinction vpon charitie and loue, these wordes of S. Augustin are founde.</head>
               <p>¶ Also the lorde. I am the lyue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly bread that came doune from heauen, if any man doth eate of
<pb facs="tcp:176398:31"/> this bread, he shal lyue for euer He therfore that doth not lyue for euer, did neuer eat this liue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly breade. But he that hath not eaten, dyd not beleue in hym. For this is to eate, that lyuelye <note place="margin">To beleue in Christ is to eate his body and to drinke his bloude.</note> breade, to beleue in Christ, that is to say, with loue, to sticke fast vnto Christe. Sith therefore y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> the wicked dyd not beleue, he did not eate hym, and so he dyd wante the faith of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Christians wherby onely sinnes are remit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Augustine, vpon the wordes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lord in Luke▪ xxviii. Sermon.</head>
               <p>¶ Geue vs this day, our dayly bread. When I dyd entreate of the sacrament, I did say vntoo you, that before the wordes of Christ, that, which is offered, is <note place="margin">Marke howe that he saith it is called y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by of Christ &amp; not it is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Christe. Christ is that supersubstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall breade.</note> bread: but after that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wordes of Christe are spoken, it is noo
<pb facs="tcp:176398:32"/> more called bread: but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of Christ. Therfore in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lords prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, which foloweth, we say: giue vs y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> supersubstancial bread, not this bread that goeth intoo the body: but that bread of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styng life, which vpholdeth the substaunce of our soule.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ This saying of S. Augustin is founde in the Canones of consecratyon, and in hys Epystle to Hierome.</head>
               <p>¶ The body of Christ, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che <note place="margin">Ergo it is not where soeuere the sacrament is ministred.</note> he did ryse, muste be in one place: but hys truthe is spreade throughout al the worlde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Augustine, in his Epistle to Dardanus.</head>
               <p>¶ Therefore doubte not, but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Iesus Christ, in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he is a man is there, frō whence he shal come, Remembre and faithfully hold the Chrystyan confessyon, that he dyd ryse from deathe, ascen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded into heauen, and sytteth on
<pb facs="tcp:176398:32"/> the ryght hande of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, <note place="margin">Thys faith or article of oure faith thei doo destroi which aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rme that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very naturall body of christ is in the sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente,</note> and that he shall come frō none other place, too iudge the quycke and the deade. And he shal come (y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> angels testifyinge y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same) as he was sene to go vp into heauē, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same fourme &amp; substaunce of flesshe, vnto the whych truelye, he dyd giue immortalitie, but frō it hee did not take away the humayn nature. After this fourme, wee <note place="margin">Heare we be warned too shunne y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resye of the Marcionites which dyd af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyrm y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Christ hath but a phantasticall body</note> must not thinke y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he is in euery place. For we must beware that we do not so affirme the diuini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of the manhod, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the truth of his body. For it foloweth not, that the thyng which is in god, shuld be in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place, as god is. For the scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture dothe truely testifye vnto vs, that we liue, moue and be in hym, &amp; yet are we not in euerye
<pb facs="tcp:176398:33"/> place, as he is. But manne is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise in god, and god other wyse in man, by a certayne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per &amp; singulare waye. For God and man is one person, &amp; bothe <note place="margin">Christ touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hod is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen &amp; in eueri place touche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed.</note> of thē one Christ Iesus, whiche is in euery place, in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he is god, and in heauen, in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he is a man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Augustine vpon Ihon, touchinge the wordes of the lorde, the .liii. Sermon.</head>
               <p>¶ The very true faythe dothe <note place="margin">The churche whiche is the mistical body of Christ, is bi a certain ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of speach called Christe</note> hold, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the sauiour of the world was sente vnto vs. For Christe him self, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say, the bodye of Christ, dispersed throughout al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world, doth preche Christ. He was in heauē, and yet vnto him that persecuted rageously here in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earth, he did say: Why dost thou persecute me? Where the lorde dyd expressely shewe, that he was here in vs. So he doth encrease and growe together
<pb facs="tcp:176398:33"/> wholle: For euen as he is in vs here, soo we are there in hym. The knotte of loue and chary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye <note place="margin">Charite doth make vs one with god.</note> dothe bringe that too passe. He that is our head, is the sauy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our of his bodye. Ergo, Christe doth preache Christ. The body doth preache his heade, and the head doth defend his body, and therfore the world hateth vs. Whosoeuer will be in his body &amp; in hys members, let him not maruayle, yf the worlde hateth him. Many do receyue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Not all they y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> receyue the sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramēt be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uede or incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated wyth Christ</note> of his body: but they shall not all that receyue it, haue the place with him,, which is promi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed vnto his members.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Augustin in his commentaries vpon the xxxiii. psalme.</head>
               <p>¶ A man may be borne with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">He dothe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfe in the .ii. sermone vpō the same psalm where he saith, he was borneaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a certaine maner in hys owne handes Moreouer this place is wel expoūded both in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che goth here before &amp; in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> whiche imme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diately folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth. Marke these allusions and maner of speakynges,</note> mens handes. Wyth hys owne handes no man is borne.
<pb facs="tcp:176398:34"/> But christ was born w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s own handes, whē he betaking his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, did say. This is mybody: for he did bear y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> body in his hands</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Augustine, to Bonifacius.</head>
               <p>¶ We often vse to say whē Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster draweth nigh, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> to morowe or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> next day, is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lordes passyō. And yet it is manye yeres since he suffered, &amp; that passyon was neuer done but ones. And vpō y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> sonday we say: This daye the lord did rise again, and yet it is many yeres since he rose. Now is there no man so folish, too re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue vs as liers, for so saying. Because we name these dayes, after the simylytude of those in which y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thinges wer done, so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it is called y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same day which is not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very day: but by reuoluti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of time, like vnto it. And it is named to be done the same day for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> celebration of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacrament
<pb facs="tcp:176398:34"/> which is not done that day, but was done long before. Was not Christ once crucified in his own person? &amp; yet in a mistery he is crucified for the people, not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly euery feast of Easter: but eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry day. Neither doth he lie, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che (whē he is asked) answereth that he is crucified. For if the sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramentes <note place="margin">The sacramē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes doo take y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> names of the verye thinges whereof they are sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> had not certain simi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litudes, of those things wherof they are sacraments, thē shuld they be noo sacramentes at all. And for this symilitude, for the most part, they take y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> names of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very thinges. And therfore af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter a certain maner, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacramēt of Christes body, is Christes bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, &amp; the sacrament of Christes bloud, is Christes bloud. And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacrament of faith, is fayth. For it is none other thing to beleue thē to haue faith. And therfore when a man aunsweareth that
<pb facs="tcp:176398:35"/> the infant beleueth (which hath not yet the affect of faith) he an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swereth that he hath fayth, for the sacramente of faithe. And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> he turneth hym selfe vnto god, for the sacrament of conuersyō. For the answere pertaineth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ministring of the sacramēt As the apostle wryteth of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme. We are buryed (saith he) <note place="margin">Baptisme sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifyeth bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng and yet y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> apostell saieth not we signifi burymge but we are buried so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> this verbe est, is, muste be here taken for it signifieth Christe in his laste Suppere dyd delyuer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> figure of hys bodi vnto his disciples.</note> w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Christ, through baptisme, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to death-He saith not: We signi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fie burying, but vtterly he saith We are buried. He called there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the sacrament of so highe a thing, euē wyth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> propre name of the very thing it selfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Augustine in the preface of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> .iii. Psal.</head>
               <p>¶ He admitted him (speakinge of Iudas) vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> banket, when he dyd betake &amp; delyuer vntoo his disciples, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> figur of his bodi</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Augustine to Adamantus. </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:176398:35"/>
               <p> ¶ The lord doubted not to say This is my body, when he <note place="margin">The lorde say<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth this is mi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>odi whan he gaue a fygure of it.</note> gaue a signe, or figure of his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye. For truely (saith he, by and by after in the same chapiter) so the bloud is the soule as Christ was the stone. And yet the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle dyd not saye: The stone did signifie Christ, but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> stone was Christe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Prosper, in the boke of sentences.</head>
               <p>¶ He that dwelleth in Christ, &amp; <note place="margin">He that by sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greethe from Christe doeth not eate hys flesshe, nor drinke hys bloude.</note> whose geast Christe is, doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meate of life, &amp; drinketh the cup of eternitie. For he that discordeth frō Christ, doth ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eate his flesshe nor drynke his blud, although he receiueth indifferently euery daye, the sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament of so high a thyng, too the condemnatyon of hys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptiousnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Ambrose vpon the sacramentes. </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:176398:36"/>
               <p> ¶ This breade that goeth into the bodye, is not soo greadelye <note place="margin">The bread of euerlastynge life is soughte of vs.</note> sought of vs, but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> breade of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlastinglife, which vpholdeth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> substaunce of the soul. For he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> disagreeth from Christe, dothe not eat his flesh, nor drinke his bloud, although he receiueth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacrament of so high a thyng, to his vtter damnatiō &amp; vndoing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Ambrose vpon y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> epistle to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Cori. xi. cha vpon this saying: Shewe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lordes death</head>
               <p>¶ Because that we wer deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by the death of the lord, we, <note place="margin">Here he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente.</note> in eating and drinkyng of thys thing, do signify the flesshe and bloud, whyche were offered for vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Ambrose, vpon the sacraments .iiii. boke</head>
               <p>But paraduenture y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> wilt say: I se no appearaunce of bloude, <note place="margin">We drynke a similitude of Christes blud</note> but it hath a similytude. For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as thou hast taken the simi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lytude
<pb facs="tcp:176398:36"/> of deathe, euen soo thou drinkest the similitude of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Tertullian in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> .ii. boke against Marcion</head>
               <p>¶ Christe hym selfe did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue <note place="margin">Marciō was an heritike which dyd re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proue al crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs saiyng y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they wer euil Marcion dyd affyrme that Christe hath a phantastical body, whiche opinion, thys holy doctour dothe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thee sacramente which coulde not haue bene a figur of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stes body, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte hee had a trewe body▪</note> or discommende breade, wher w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he doth represent hys bodye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Tertullian, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> .iiii. boke against Marciō</head>
               <p>¶ Christ taking bread, &amp; distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butinge it vntoo hys disciples made it his bodi, saiing. This is my body, that is to say, the fygure of my bodye: But thys bread could not haue bene a fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of it, except christ had had a true bodye. For a vaine thing or phantastycall can take noo fygure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Origene vpon Leuiticus, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> .vii. Homely.</head>
               <p>¶ Vnderstande that they are fygures, whyche are wrytten in the Scryptures of GOD.
<pb facs="tcp:176398:37"/> And therfore examine them, as spirytuall men, and not as car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. Vnderstand those thinges which are spoken-For if ye take or vnderstand those thinges as carnall men, they do hurte, and not nourysshe. For there is also in the gospell, a letter y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> killeth. Not onely in the old testament <note place="margin">In the newe testamēt there is also a letter that killeth.</note> a killing letter is found: but also there is in the new testament, a letter which killeth him, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> doth not vnderstande those thinges spirituallye, whiche are spoken. For if thou doest folowe after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> letter, thys that is spoken: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <note place="margin">Iho. vi. chap.</note> ye eat my flesh and drynke my bloude, thys letter killethe. Wilt thou that I bryng vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> out of the new testament, an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther letter y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> kylleth? He y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hath no knife (saith he) let him sel his cote &amp; bie one. Lo, this letter is <note place="margin">Luke .xxii. cha</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176398:37"/> of the gospell, and yet it killeth But if thou takest it spiritually it kylleth not: but in it is a quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening spirit. Therefore vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stand spiritually those thynges whyche are spoken, whether it be in the lawe, or in the gospell For a spirytuall man dyscusseth al thynges, and is iudged of no man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>In the same boke, the .ix. Homelye.</head>
               <p>And thou whych art come to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> true bisshop which w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his bloud hath purchased vnto the, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy of god, &amp; hath reconciled the vnto his father, doo not stycke to the bloud of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flesh: but lerne rather the bloud of the worde. And heare him that saythe.</p>
               <p>This is my bloud whych <note place="margin">The flesh and blud of godes word must be sought.</note> shal be shed, for the remis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>syon of youre synnes. He
<pb facs="tcp:176398:38"/> which is taught in the mistery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, doth know the flesh &amp; bloud of the word of god.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Athanasius vpō this saying of Christ, he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> shall speake a word against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy gost</head>
               <p>¶ It is the spirit that quycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, the flesh profiteth nothing <note place="margin">Ihon .vi. cha</note> the wordes whych I spake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too you, are spirite &amp; life. For in this place also he meaneth both of his own flesh, &amp; his owne spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: And he deuideth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> spirit frō the flesh, that they might know through faith, not onely the visi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble part, but also y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> inuisible part that was in him,, &amp; also that the words which he spake, wer not carnal, but spirituall. For what bodi shuld haue suffised, to haue <note place="margin">No carnal bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy can suffice to be y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> meate of all the worlde</note> bene y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meat of al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world? And therfore did he make mentiō of the goyng vp of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> son of man in to heauen, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he might w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> drawe
<pb facs="tcp:176398:38"/> thē, frō the bodely imagination and y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they might herafter lern <note place="margin">Why Christ dyd make mē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of his as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendyng into heauen.</note> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the flesh was called heauenly meat, whych commeth from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, &amp; the spiritual meat why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he wold geue. For (saith he) the wordes that I haue spoken <note place="margin">Ihon .vi. cha</note> vnto you, are spirite and lyfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Bede vpon Luke.</head>
               <p>¶ After y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> solempnitie of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> olde <note place="margin">Why y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> solem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Eas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lamb was kepte</note> Easter lamb was finisshed, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was obserued in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> memory al of the old deliueraūce oute of Egipt, he passeth furth vnto the new (which y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church gladly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serueth in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> remembraunce of their redemptiō) y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> stead <note place="margin">Christ did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of his owne fleshe &amp; bloude, in the figur of bread and wyne.</note> of the flesh &amp; bloud of the lambe might institute &amp; ordain the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his own flesshe and blud, in the figure of bread and wine, &amp; so declare him self, to be the same vnto whom the lorde sware.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:176398:39"/>
               <p> Thou art a perpetual priest, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ordre of Melchisedeche And he him self brake the bread which he gaue, to shew that the breaking of his body, shuld not be done without his wyll. And <note place="margin">The breaking of christes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye was nott done without hys will. Why y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bread is referred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the wine vnto his bloude.</note> likewise he gaue thē the cup, af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter he had supped. And because bread doth confyrme and corro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>borate the flesh, and wyne wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth bloud in the flesshe: There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore is the bread misticallye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred vnto the body of Christ, and the wyne vnto his bloude.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Barnard, vpon the psalme, qui habitat: the third verse, and the .iii. Sermon.</head>
               <p>¶ Except ye eat the flesh of the <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hon .vi. cha.</note> son of man &amp; drinke his blud. &amp;c They said: This is a harde say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and so went away backe frō him: But what is it to eate hys flesh, and to drinke hys bloude: but to be partakers of his passi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:176398:39"/> and to folow that conuersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whiche he dyd vse here in the flesh? Which thyng y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> moste holy sacrament, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whiche we <note place="margin">The bread en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treth into the mouthe, but Christe into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hearte.</note> receyue the bodye of the lorde, doth signifie, that is to say, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> as the forme of bread is sene to en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tre into vs, so we must knowe, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> by that conuersation, whych he did vse in the earth, he entreth into vs, to dwell, through faith in our heartes. For when righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes dothe entre, he dothe <note place="margin">i. Corinthi. i.</note> entre also, whiche of god the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is made vntoo vs ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Gelasius Bishop of Rome, againste the Entichians in the councyle of Rome.</head>
               <p>¶ Surely the sacramentes of the body and bloud of Chryste, are godly and diuine thinges, &amp; therfore through them, are we made partakers of the diuyne.
<pb facs="tcp:176398:40"/> &amp; godly nature. And yet dothe <note place="margin">Thys surelye was the olde learning whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til craft of the deuyl was subuerted.</note> it doth not cease too be the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce of breade and wine, but contynue stil in the propertie of their owne nature. And surely, the image and similitude of the body and bloud of Christ, are ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lebrated in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> act of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> misteries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Fulgentius, in the seconde boke of faith</head>
               <p>¶ In these carnal sacrifices, in <note place="margin">As the sacryfi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of the old lawe were sha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dowes of the flesh of Christ which should be offred, so y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacrament is a figure of it be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng alredy of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fered. Marke y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hee doth cal it a sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice, which neuertheles is but a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nely sacrifice</note> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> time of the law, was a signify<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flesh of Christ, which he w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>out sin, shuld offer for our sinnes, &amp; of the bloud, which he shuld shede for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> remissiō of our sinnes: But thys sacryfyce is of thankes geuinge &amp; remēbraūce of the flesh of Christ, which he of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fered for vs, &amp; of the bloud, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same god did shede for vs</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>¶ Idem, in his boke to kinge Thrasy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundus.</head>
               <p>¶ This cup or chalice, is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> new testament: y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to say, this cup
<pb facs="tcp:176398:40"/> or chalice, which I deliuer vnto you, doth signifi y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> new testamēt</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Idem in the second boke.</head>
               <p>The same one man is local as <note place="margin">Christ beinge a man is lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, that is to saye is cōtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in one place onely.</note> touching his manhod, which is also God vnmeasurable frō the father. Thesame one mā, as tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching the substaūce of his man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hod, was absent from heauen, when he was in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earth: &amp; forsa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earth when he ascended into heauen: But as touchinge his godheade, &amp; vnmeasurable substaunce, he neyther forsoke heauen, when he descended frō heauē, nor forsoke y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earth, whē he ascended into heauē. Whych maye be knowen by this moste <note place="margin">How Christe did shewe his humanitye to bee locall and his godheade to be presente in euery place</note> sure worde of the Lorde, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che to shewe hys humanytie, to be contained in one place onely dyd saye vntoo his disciples. I ascend vnto my father, &amp; youre father, my God, and your God.
<pb facs="tcp:176398:41"/> Of Lazarus also, when he said Lazarus is dead. He saide fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more: I am glad for youre sakes (that ye myghte beleue) y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I was not there. And agayne, shewing the vnmeasurablenes of his godhed, he said vnto hys disciples: Beholde, I am wyth you to the worldes ende. How did he ascende into heauen: but because he was locall, and a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man? Or how is he presente vnto his faithfull: but because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he is vnmeasurable, and verye God?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Hierome in his cōmentaries vpon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe .xxvi. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>¶ After y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the mystycall Easter lambe was fulfylled, and that Christe had eaten the lambes flesh, with his Apostles, he toke breade, whyche conforteth the hert of man, and passeth furthe
<pb facs="tcp:176398:41"/> to the true sacrament of the Ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ster <note place="margin">Here Hierom w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> holy Tertu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lian doth hold against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tike Marcion</note> lambe, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> as Melchisedeche brought furth bread and wyne in prefiguratyon of hym, soo he myght lykewyse represente the truth of his bodye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Hierom vpon Ecclesiastes, that is to say the boke of the preacher</head>
               <p>¶ The flesh of the lord is very meate, and the bloud of the lord <note place="margin">We do eate y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of Christ and drinke his bloud in the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge of the scriptures.</note> is verye drinke. We haue thys good or profyte onelye, in thys worlde, that we maye eate hys flesh, and drynke hys bloud, not onely in a misterye, but alsoo in the readyng of the scryptures. For it is very meat and drinke, which is taken oute of goddes word, by the knowledge of the scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>❧ Hierome vpon the .C. ix. Psalme. and .viii. Tome.</head>
               <p>¶ Thou art a perpetual priest,
<pb facs="tcp:176398:42"/> after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ordre of Melchisedeche Let vs declare onely, whye he did say, after the order of Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisedech. Thys trewlye is as muche to say: Thou shalt not be a priest after the Iuisshe oblaty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons: But thou shalt be a prieste after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> order of Melchisedeche For as Melchisedech dyd offer or bring furth bread and wyne, <note place="margin">The bodye &amp; bloud of christ is the trewe breade &amp; the trew wine Melchisa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech was kynge of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</note> so thou shalt offer thy body, and thy bloude, whych is the trewe bread and wyne. Thys Melchi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sedech did giue those mysteries that we haue, vntoo vs. It is he that sayde: He that eatethe my flesshe, and drynketh mye bloude. &amp;c. After the ordre of Melchisedech, he dyd gyue his sacrament vnto vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>☞ Hierom in his cōmentaries vpon the Epistle of Paule to the Ephesyans.</head>
               <p>¶ The flesh and blud of Chryst
<pb facs="tcp:176398:42"/> is taken or vnderstanded .ii. wai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es. <note place="margin">The flesh and blud of Christ is vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded .ii. wayes</note> Either that spirituall and di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uine flesh, of the which he saith: My flesh is verye meate, &amp; my bloud is verye drynke. Or that flesh which was crucyfyed, or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bloud which was shed with the speare of the souldyer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>❧ Chrisostom. vpon the .xxvi. of Mat.</head>
               <p>¶ He also dranke of it, lest whē they hearde hys wordes, they <note place="margin">Chryste hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>self did drinke of the cuppe a fore y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he gaue it to his apos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles.</note> should saye: Why? doo we then drinke bloude, and eate flesh? &amp; so should be troubled, for when he spake before of those thyngs they were offended wyth hys wordes. And because it shoulde not nowe alsoo chaunce, he him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfe dranke fyrste of it, that he mighte cause them to come w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute feare too the partaking of those mysteryes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:176398:43"/>
               <head>❧ Idem .xvi. Homelye</head>
               <p>¶ The flesh profyteth nothing <note place="margin">Ihon .vi. cha</note> That is too saye: My wordes must be vnderstanded after the spirite. He that vnderstandeth them after the flesh; winneth no thing, nor taketh no profit ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of. What meaneth this, too vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande after the flesh, or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally? <note place="margin">What is to vnderstand af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the flesshe</note> Verely to take the thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges simplie, as they are spoken and thynke none other thinge. All mysteries or sacramentes, must be considered w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> inwarde eyes, that is to say, spirituallie. For the inward eies as sone as they do se the bread, do passe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the creatures, and thynke not of that bread which is bakē <note place="margin">That heauen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly bread whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is Christe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s signified by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacramente</note> of the baker: but of him that cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led him selfe the breade of lyfe, which is signified by the mysty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>call or sacramentall breade.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:176398:43"/>
               <head>❧ Chrisostom in his first Tome vpon y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> viii. chapiter of Mathew, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>. xvi homelie.</head>
               <p>¶ It is against all reason, that we in verye dede enioying hys benefites dayly, shoulde not as muche as w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> wordes, giue hym thankes: Sith that the same ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knowledging <note place="margin">The acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledgynge of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> benyfites of god doth pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite vs.</note> &amp; confession doth profit vnto vs. For he hath noo nede of any thing that is ours, but we haue nede of all that he hath. The giuynge of thankes addeth nothing vntoo him: but it maketh vs more familyares vnto his maiestie. For syth that when we remembre the benefy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of mē, we are the vehement lyer inflamed &amp; kindeled, wyth the loue of them: Muche more <note place="margin">Collo. iii. Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> if we be mindfull of the benefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of god, we shall be the more studious to kepe his cōmaunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments. Therfore y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> apostle saith
<pb facs="tcp:176398:44"/> Be ye thankful. For the remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce of benefits &amp; perpetual thankes geuing, is a very good keper of benefits: wherfor these most reuerent &amp; holsom misteri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es, which we do celebrate in eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye congregatyon, are called <note place="margin">Why y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is called <hi>Eucharistia.</hi>
                  </note> Eucharistia, that is too saye thankes geuynge. For they are the remembraunce of many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefytes, and shew the head foū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> diulne charitie &amp; loue toward vs, &amp; causevs alwaies to giue due thankes vnto god.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>☞ Chrisostome vpon the .x. Chapyter, to the Hebrues, and .xvii. Homelye.</head>
               <p>¶ And thys that we do, we do in the remembraunce of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is done alreadye. For (saith he) do this in the remembraūce of me. We do not offer an other sacryfyce (as the Bisshop of the olde lawe) but alwaies the selfe
<pb facs="tcp:176398:44"/> same, yea, rather we doo worke the memoryall &amp; remembraūce <note place="margin">Here holy Chrisostome and all other faythefull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doo vse thys worde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> sacrifice for a memoriall &amp; remēbraunce of that onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> sacrifice ones offred for euer as Augusty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> also witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>. xxx viii. boke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst Faus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus much con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to them which craftely haue brought and induced into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church of Christ this cursed sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> mass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> of that sacryfyce: But because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I haue made mentyon of thys sacryfyce. I wyll speake fewe thynges vntoo you, fewe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in numbre and measure: but whiche haue greate vertue and vtilitie. Whiche remembre ye, and prynt in youre mindes. For the thinges that are spokē, be not ours, but the holy gostes What be they thē? Very many do receiue of this sacrifice ones in the wholl yeare, some twyse, some oftener. Therefore we generally to al, not onely to thē y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> be here: but also to thē y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> sit in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wildernes. For they do party<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipate ones in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yeare, yea, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaūce after two yeares: What then? Whome doo we accepte most? Them that receiue it but ones, or them y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> receyue it often
<pb facs="tcp:176398:45"/> or them that communycate sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? Verelye we neyther ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them that receyue it ones, <note place="margin">They y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> come to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lordes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a pure conscience are to be prefered before al other and to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</note> nor them that receyue it often, nor them that communicate sel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, but them that come vnto it wyth a pure conscyence, with a cleane heart, with a blameles life. And they that are not such, do not receyue it as much as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: why so? for they do receiue their own dampnation and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>▪ Cor. xi. cha</note> vndoyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>☞ Chrisostome out of the oratyon of S. Philogonius.</head>
               <p>¶ Many christen men are now come to y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> madnes, and are gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen to so great a contempte, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> where as they be ful of innume<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable vyces, they nothynge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard <note place="margin">The tyme of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cōmunyon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s no holy day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut of pure cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ience.</note> their own life, but vpō ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly daies, do come negligently &amp; rechelously vntoo this bourde,
<pb facs="tcp:176398:45"/> not knowing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the time, of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, is neither holy day nor solempnitie: but a pure conscy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp; a life cleane from sinnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>☞ Chrisostome out of the .xxvii. homelie touchinge his retourne from Asia to Constantinopol.</head>
               <p>¶ We are not like the Iues, we <note place="margin">In y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> matter of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacramēt we are ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bound to place nor to tyme.</note> are neither subiect to place nor to time, being confirmed w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the saying of the lord. As oftē (saith he) as ye eat of this breade, and drinke of this cup, ye shal shewe furth the lordes death. To day then we shew the lordes death: But then an holy day, &amp; now to day also a holy day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>☞ Chrisostō in his .i. Tome .li. Homelie,</head>
               <p>¶ For this sacrament is a sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mēt <note place="margin">The sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente of peace.</note> of peace, which doth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre with couetousnes of money nor with simonie. For if he dyd not spare him self for our sakes
<pb facs="tcp:176398:46"/> what punishment do we not de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>serue, if we spare not our soules <note place="margin">Iudas for co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiteousnes of money sould Christ, and so he did perissh Simon wold haue boughte the gyfte of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy ghost for money, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hee myght be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched therby wherefore all they that bye or sel any spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall giftes for lucre and money are called after thys Simon Magus Simoniakes. The trew ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure of thys sacrifyce.</note> for the which Christe dyd gyue him selfe, and in the meane sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son do spare money? Therfore let no Iudas nor Simon come to that table which both did pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rish for couetousnes of money. Wherfore let vs I pray, auoyd and exchew this parilouse pyt, nor let vs not thynke that it is sufficient for oure saluatyon, yf when we haue spoyled wyddo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes and fatherles children, we offer vnto this table, a chalice of gold, trimmed wyth precyouse stones. Wilt thou honour thys sacryfyce? Offer thy soule, for y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> whiche Christe was crucyfyed, make it golden. For if thy soule be a vessell of leade, what shall golden vessels profyte thee?</p>
               <p>And verelye that (table was <note place="margin">Superfluouse coste in chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches is discom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mendyd.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176398:46"/> not of siluer, nor that chalice of gold, wherin christ did giue his blud, to his disciples, and yet al thynges wer precyous, &amp; ful of veneration and worshippe. For they were ful of the spirit. Wilt thou worship y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of Christ? <note place="margin">How y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> body of Christ must be worshiped</note> Despyse hym not naked in hys members, nor do not cloth him with sylkes in the churche, and suffer him negligentlye abrode to be storued for colde and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes. For he y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saeth: Thys is my body, and together w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                  <note place="margin">Vnderstande here that as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lambe beyng taken oute of the flocke and applied to the sacrifices of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> passeouer is called y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> passe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer of the lorde so is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bread whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is broken in the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of the body of Christe called the body of Christ. It is the grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>test honour y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we can do vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to god, if we do fulfyll his wil &amp; worship him as he hath taughte vs in his word</note> the worde, dyd bryng the thing to passe, sayth also: ye haue sene me hungrye, and yee haue not fedde me. And in so muche that ye dydde not it too one of these little ones, ye dydde it not vnto mee, </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:176398:47"/>
               <p> this body of Christ (meanyng y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which is ministred in the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) hath no nede of gayeclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other body (here he doth vnderstand the poor mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bres of Christe) hath neade of greate care and dilygence. Let vs therefore learne to be trew phylosophers in Christe Iesu, and to worshyp hym after hys owne wyll. For he whyche is worshypped, delyteth moste in that worshyppe, whiche he him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfe wyll haue, not in that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we prescribe vnto him, So Peter thought that he dyd ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure Christe, when he woulde not suffre him to wash his fete: but it was contrarie. Likewise worshyppe thou hym, as he wil be worshypped, laye abrode thy ryches too the poore. There is noo neade of golden vessels, but
<pb facs="tcp:176398:47"/> of golden soules. Aunswere me (I pray) what profit is it, if whē his table in decked wyth many suche golden cuppes, he him self perissheth for hunger? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">The poore must be cared for afore al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges.</note> fede hym firste, and after y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> shalt decke his table, as of a su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabundaunce. Thou doste make him a chalice of gold, and thou wilt not geue him a cup of cold water. What profite doth folow therof? The couerynges <note place="margin">Thys godlye lerninge hath bene long hid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</note> of his table, do shine with golde and y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> denaiest vnto him necessa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry raymentes. What dost thou geue him then? Cell me, I pray the, if thou shouldest se a man al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>most dead for hunger, and wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest not succour his necessitye, wyth some meate: but decke a table before hym wyth muche golde and syluer? What than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes thinkest thou would y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> man giue vnto the? What if y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deste
<pb facs="tcp:176398:48"/> se a man almoste frosen w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> cold, &amp; woldest prepare no neces<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sary raimēts for him, but set vp goldē images in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> honor of him shuldest y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> not seme to cōtempne him? So it behoueth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> to think in Christ. When he goeth about wandering, as a straunger, lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king harbor, then y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> dost not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue hym, &amp; in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mean season, y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> dost trim y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pauings of churches Thou makest vp costly walles, y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> settest vp gorgious heades of pillars, thou causest lampes to hang down frō golden sielyngs &amp; in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mean season thou dost not visite him being in prison. Noo <note place="margin">No man was euer blamede because he had not buylded gorgious churchis</note> man was euer blamed or accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed because he had not buylded vp costly temples or churches. But euerlasting fire of hel (y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nishment of the deuils) do hang ouer vs, except we doo thother thinges diligentlye.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb facs="tcp:176398:48"/>
            <head>¶ To all theim y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> truth and veritie of our lord, Ihon Veron wissheth grace, not onelye to be readers, but also to be true folowers of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gospell of our sauiour Iesu Christ, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> so we may al w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a clere conscience, come too the lordes table, banket &amp; feaste of euerlastynge life.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere ye haue (good chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stē readers) y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> opinyons &amp; sayinges of the olde faithfull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vpon the Sacrament of the body and bloude of Christe, compendyouslye sette forthe: Whereby ye may vnderstande and perceiue, not onelye howe we haue bene deceiued in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sacrament, these manye hundreth yeres, by certain false
<pb facs="tcp:176398:49"/> prophetes, yet remayning here emong vs in this world, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so how we ought, if we entende to be in the vnitie of the bodye: of Christ, to come vnto this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maundie, and banket of euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lasting saluation. Verelye, dere beloued brethren, I wold wish that all we, that do professe the gospell had alwayes when we come to this communion, that most holsome and profitable sai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng of the apostle, in our memo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye and remembraunce: Purge the olde leuen, that ye maye be <note place="margin">i. Cor, v. cha</note> swete dowe, as ye are swete bread. For Christ our passeouer is offered vp for vs. Therefore let vs kepe holy daye, not wyth olde leauen, neyther wyth the leauen of malycyousenes &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kednes: but w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the swete bread of purenes &amp; truth: Then shuld
<pb facs="tcp:176398:49"/> all enuye, malyce and rancoure al fylthy liuing and communica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, al couetousnes, fornicatiō, adultery, &amp; abhominable whor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, all detestable swearynge strife and altercatyon be banys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed away from oure heartes. Then shuld the mouthes of the enemies of the crosse of Christe <note place="margin">The enemyes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> truthe, do take an occasi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on vpon oure naughtye ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, to blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures.</note> and of his gospel, whyche vpon our wicked and filthy lyuynge, do take an occasion to speake e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyl of the worde of God, and of hys moste sacred Scriptures, too the greate comforte of all godly persons, be vtterly stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. Ye shal vnderstand, that in this place the holy apostle saint Paule doth allude to that olde sacrament of the paschal lambe; or passeouer, which y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> aunciente Iues were cōmaunded to kepe in the memorial of their delyue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunce
<pb facs="tcp:176398:50"/> oute of Egipte. In thys olde fygure, nothyng was com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded so strayghtlye, as the vnleuened breade. In so muche that the lorde doth by hys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Moses saye. Whosoeuer <note place="margin">Exo. xii. Cha.</note> shall vpon these dayes eate any leuened breade, hys soule shall perisshe, frō emonge my people. This was but a figure, brethrē <note place="margin">Mat. xvi. cha. Beware of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> leuen of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rises and sadu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. v. chapi Know ye not y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a litle leuen dothe sowre y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whole lumpe of dowe?</note> of better thynges to come. For sithe that leauen in the scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, when it is taken in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worse parte, doth sygnyfye bothe the hipocritical doctrin of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye, and alsoo wycked and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean conditiōs wherw<seg rend="sup">t</seg> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whol man, yea the whole societie and felowshyp of mankynd is infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. It is euydente, that nowe when Christ oure true paschall lambe, is reuelated vntoo the worlde: we ought to kepe a per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petuall
<pb facs="tcp:176398:50"/> passeouer, abstainyng al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>waies from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> leuen of vngodly doctrine, &amp; vnpure life. Which if we do not, with al our might and eudeuoure, sith that we do now dayly eat our true paschal lambe or passeouer, that is too saye, feade vpon the bodye and <note place="margin">We fede dail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vpon the bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and bloude of christ spiritual<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly not in a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery only, but in the reading &amp; heringe of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scripture.</note> bloud of Christ spirituallye, not onely in a misterye, but alsoo in reading and hearing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res: we oughte too loke for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elles trulye, then for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme damnation &amp; death. For why? This is that roial &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie banket, vnto the which al na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions are bidden and inuitated But if any mā doth presume to come vnto it, not hauing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding raimēt or bridegromes li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery, he is by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> straighte cōmaū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement of that mightye kynge, which can kil both the soule and <note place="margin">Mat. xxii. cha</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:176398:51"/> the body, cast into vtter darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, where shal be wepyng and gnasshyng, of teth. Therfore yf we wil come to the lordes table <note place="margin">He that wyll come to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des table w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ieoperdye must haue vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on hym the brydegromes liuerye.</note> without ieopardie, if we wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue there an holsome repaste and not deadly poison, let vs ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amine truely oure selues, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we haue that vesture, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is requyred of thē that are bidden to that feaste, or not. By y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lyuerie badge or cogneysaūce greate Lordes seruauntes are knowen. Heare then what the lord saith: By this shall all men <note place="margin">Ihō. xiii. cha. Which is the brydegromes liuerye.</note> know, that ye are my dyscyples if ye loue one an other. Hereby ye maye perceiue that loue is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> onely rayment or liuerye, with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out the which whosoeuer dare come to this feast, he shal be, vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to his own damnatyō, cast<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>awaye, as an vnprofytable and
<pb facs="tcp:176398:51"/> rotten membre. For Paul saith Thoughe I hadde al fayth soo that I could moue mountains out of their own places, and yet <note place="margin">i. Cor. xiii. cha</note> haue noo loue, I am nothinge.</p>
            <p>Yea, though I bestowe al my goodes too fede the poore, and gyue my bodye too be brente, &amp; yet haue no loue, it profyteth me nothing. Surely withoute loue, we are vnprofitable &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruictful braunches, and be not in that knot of vnitie and peace which by thys holy sacramente is vnto vs represented. Let vs therfore caste awaye the dedes and workes of darkenes (why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the liuerie of our old aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyente <note place="margin">Rom. xiii. cha The workes of darknes be the liuerye of the deuill.</note> enemye) and put on the armour of light. Let vs walke honestly, as it were in the daye light, not in eating drynkinge neyther in chaumbring &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnes,
<pb facs="tcp:176398:52"/> neither in strife and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyinge: But putte we on Iesu Christ. He that doth put on Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>su Christe, as he shoulde do, or cast away the workes of darke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and of the flesshe, which are these: adultery, fornication, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes, wantonnes, worshyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge <note place="margin">Gala. v. chap</note> of idoles, witchcrafte, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, variaunce, wrath, strife, se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dition, sectes, enuying, murder, dronkennes, glotony, and suche <note place="margin">What hee doth put on, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> putteth on Christe Galat. v. chap</note> like: so he doth put on, and take to him selfe: loue, peace, vnitye, concord, longe suffering, gentle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, goodnes, faithfulnes, meke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, temperauncye: brieflye, he doth put on all godly vertues, required of vs in the Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and worde of God. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer is decked wyth suche a vesture and lyuerye, let hym come boldelye to the lordes sup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per,
<pb facs="tcp:176398:52"/> and there he shall tast how swete the lorde is, there he shall receyue that lyuelye breade, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> fedeth to euerlastinge life Some wil paraduenture saye: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> Thys is a straunge doctryne and contrarye to all scriptures Doth not Saincte Paule saye <note place="margin">Roma. i. chap Gala. ii. chap</note> that the ryghteouse shall lyue by faythe? Doth not oure iusti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fycatyon depende of faythe one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye? Then yf we brynge faythe to the lordes table, it is sufficy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente to oure saluatyon? There shall we receiue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> most holsome phisicke y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> healeth all the dysea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of the soul, and at length we shall heare y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> moste comfortable word &amp; saiing of our lord Iesus christ: go thy way, thy faith hath <note place="margin">Mat. ix. chap Solution By faith only we are iusty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed. Here y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> must marke y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thys worde only added of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holi doctors do not exclud good workes as thoughe whē we haue faith we shuld do nothynge, but it exclude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ostētation and bostynge of oure good dedes. Bryef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye we muste worke, &amp; yet saye that wee are vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble seruaūtes and y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> through oure workes we meryt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge. Gala. v. chapi Ephe. ii. chap</note> made y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> safe. I confesse &amp; graūt &amp; euer haue bene of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> opinion &amp; mynd, that fayth in Iesu Christ
<pb facs="tcp:176398:53"/> doth iustifye without the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the law. For fayth is the onely meate, wherby we appre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hend the mercy of god, trust to his promises and his word. By fayth onely we are saued, oure sinnes are forgiuen, and before God we be accompted ryghtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouse, as the Apostle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, and Galathians dothe plainly testifie. But thys faithe must be no dead faith, it must be liuely, it must worke and bringe forth fruictes worthy this our vocation and calling. For saint Paule saith: In Iesu Christ, nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther is circumsion anye thinge nor yet vncircumcisiō: but faith which worketh by loue. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne: We are hys workeman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyp, created in Christ Iesu, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to good workes, whyche God ordained, that we shuld walk in
<pb facs="tcp:176398:53"/> them. Whych (I praye the) are those good workes? These ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely are the good workes whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che <note place="margin">The good workes y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> god dothe require of vs much cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trarye to the doctrine of Antichriste which taught y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Masses pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grymages &amp; such beggerly geare were good workes</note> god hath ordained that we should walke in them al the dai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of our life. To be in outward and exteryoure matters nexte vnto god, subiect vnto our kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges magistrates, and rulers to honoure father and mother, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> all trewe obedyence due vntoo them. To fede the hungrie, too geue drinke to the thirstye, too cloth the naked, to harbour the harbourles, too vysite the sicke and refresshe theym that be in pryson. Bryeflye too loue oure neyghbour as oure selues, and to do alwaies vntoo other, as we wyll be done too. These be the workes preciselye commaū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded of God in hys worde and Scryptures, whiche yf we doo
<pb facs="tcp:176398:54"/> not too the vttermoste of oure power, the dreadfull iudge Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christe, whome wee haue despysed in hys members, shall thunder vpon vs that dreade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ineuytable Sentence. Departe ye from me (O ye cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed) intoo euerlasting fyre, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is prepared for the deuyll, and hys aungelles. Not ye all <note place="margin">Mat. xxv. cha</note> that saye vntoo mee, Lorde, Lorde, shall enter intoo the kyngedome of heauen: but he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> doth the wyl of my father, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is in heauen, he shall enter to the kyngdom of heauē: Had not these folkes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gift of faithe? Marke what foloweth. They shall saye vntoo mee, Lorde, Lorde, haue we not prophecy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed in thy name? Haue we not caste oute deuils, and done ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:176398:54"/> great myracles through it? And then sayth Christe, I wyll acknowledge vnto them: I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer knewe you. Departe from <note place="margin">Mat. vii. chap</note> me, ye that worke iniquytye. Surelye these personnes, here mentioned of, by our sauyoure Iesus Christe, had beside fayth (wythoute the whyche they coulde notte haue done those myracles) the gyfte of prophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sye. Whye are they then reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tede and caste awaye? Because verelye, that they wanted loue. For the holye Apostle Saincte Paul (as I haue already, alled<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged before) dothe paynlye say. <note place="margin">i. Cori. xiii. ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Thoughe I coulde prophecye and vnderstande all mysteryes or secretes and all knowledge. Yea, though I haue al fayth, so that I could moue moūtaynes oute of their owne places, and
<pb facs="tcp:176398:55"/> yet haue no loue, I am nothing Wilt thou say (here I do speake generally vnto all them that w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> vs doo prefesse the gospell) that thou hast a Christian faith, whē thou seest thy brother or thy si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <note place="margin">He that seeth his brother or his syster na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed or destitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed of daylye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ode, &amp; hathe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o compassiō <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon theym <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath no chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian faythe.</note> naked, and destituted o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly fode (whereas thou thy selfe doste fare delycyouslye, muche meat and drinke, which in time can not be spēt of thy houshold seruauntes, being corrupted by the, many gaye and costly ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes also, beyng shamefullye moth eaten) and hast no maner of compassion vpon them? Is it inough to say vnto them, when thou shewest no mercy, nor gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest nothing vnto them: depart yee in peace: God sende you warmenes and foode? Verelye ye ryche men, ye shal wepe and howle, on youre wretchednes,
<pb facs="tcp:176398:55"/> that shal come vpon you. Your ryches are corrupte, youre gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes <note place="margin">Iam. v. Cha.</note> are moth eaten. Your golde and syluer is cankered, and the ruste of them shall bear wytnes agaynste you, and shall eate your flesh, as if it were fire Ye haue heaped treasures to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, euen wrathe too youre selues in the last dayes. Canne ye. I beseche you, affirme true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye that yee beleue in Chryste, whom ye suffer, for mere naked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and wante of fode, thus mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sexablye too perysshe? Whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is done here vnto his poor members (in whome hee is ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther refresshed or neglected) he dothe impute it done vntoo hym selfe. For saythe he: In soo muche that ye dyd it too one of these lyttleones, ye dyd it vnto me. And in soo muche as ye did <note place="margin">Mat. xxv. ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:176398:56"/> not it too one of these lyttleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ye dyd it not vntoo mee. Agayne, vntoo Saule, whyche persecuted hys churche rage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouselye here in the earthe, he sayde from heauen: Saule, Saule, whye doest thou perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute <note place="margin">Actes. ix. and xxii. Chapiter.</note> mee? Marke ye thys, ye worldelynges, whych of vncha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytable coueteousenesse, doo ioyne fielde to fielde, house too house, goyng aboute too be lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and possessyoners of all the world, whensoeuer ye put anye poore man by his lyuing, thrus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng hym oute of hys house or farme, or els cause hym to paye an vnreasonable rent &amp; income for it, therby (besides y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dearthe of all thynges, that ye cause in thys realme, through your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saciable auarice) bringinge him hys poore wyfe, and hys chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb facs="tcp:176398:56"/> to the staffe and wallette: verelye ye do it vntoo Christe. For whatsoeuer (saythe he) ye <note place="margin">Mat. xxv. cha</note> doo to one of these litleones, ye do it vntoo mee. Howe can you nowe wyth a good, and cleare conscience, thoughe ye boste ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer soo muche of youre faythe, come to this roial feast and ban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ket, not hauing one thrid of this wedding rayment, or bridegro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes lyuery vpon you. For if ye had any sparke of loue and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie <note place="margin">Vnchartytable<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes is cause y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the pore cōmo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes be so vsed.</note> in you, ye would not so or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre the poore selye membres of Christ. Your fayth is vayne, &amp; your knowledge is playn vani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye. For he that sayth. I knowe god and kepeth not his cōmaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes, <note place="margin">. i Iho. iii.</note> he is a lyer▪ and the verytye is notte in hym. But the chyefe commaundemente, yea, the somme and effect of al
<pb facs="tcp:176398:57"/> commaundementes is: Loue thy neighboure as thy own self Sith therfore that ye oppresse thus your poor neighbours, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer (as greadye horse leaches) suckyng their very bloud: yf ye say that ye knowe God, ye are but lyers, &amp; the veritye, though ye speake neuer so godly of god and his worde, is not in you. Here I do passe ouer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vnclean<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly fornication, the innumerable stinkyig adultries, and blasphe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mouse swearynges, the dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes and glotony, which reyg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth emong you, which should be the lyghtes and Lanternes of all the worlde. Yea, whyche is more too be lamented of all men, manye of you, when they haue done euyll, doo bost them selues moste shamefullye of it, and reioyce in their wicked and
<pb facs="tcp:176398:57"/> flagitiouse doinges and factes.</p>
            <p>Some agayne wyll make the <note place="margin">In the .vii. chapiter. of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> firste epistle to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> corinthians you shal finde suche a saying but note and marke why it is spoken of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> apostle. In y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ix. chapiter of Salomones prouerbes a rechelesse wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wyse<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man, whyche vngodly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth call vntoo her, such as do fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thyr ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> waies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>syng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> suche wordes as these vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly do al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge for their excuses .i. Cor. vi. chap</note> worde of God, and hys sacred scriptures a cloke, shield and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fence of their filthy liuinge. For saith the one, it is wrytten, doo whatsoeuer thou wilte, y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> shalte not synne. And the other, Salo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon affyrmeth, that stolen wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters be swete, &amp; that the bread, whyche is preuelye eaten, hath a good taste. Thus they goo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute too excuse them selues, &amp; to make the ignoraunte too be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, that the Scryptures doo beare with them in their filthy &amp; abhomynable doinges. But brethren, be not yee deceyued. For neyther fornycatours, ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther worshyppers of Images, nor aduouterers, nor weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges, nor abusers of theym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selues with mankinde, nor the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,
<pb facs="tcp:176398:58"/> nor coueteouse personnes nor dronkerdes, nor cursed spea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kers, nor extortyoners, shall en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heryte the kingedome of God. Yf oure earthelye parentes shoulde threaten at anye tyme, too dysheryte vs for oure wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vnthryftye liuyng, we wold incontynently, rather thē we wold lose our trāsitory and corruptible patrimonie, forsake all vnthryftynes. Howe muche more oughte we, sythe that our heauenly father doth threaten, that he wyll exclud vs from his kyngdome, yf we be fornycatou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, worshyppers of Images, adulterers, coueteouse, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortyoners, too forsake al these abhominable vices, and that by tyme, least we be put from that heuenly heritage, which Christ the sonne of the lyuynge God,
<pb facs="tcp:176398:58"/> hath purchased vntoo vs, with hys precyous deathe &amp; bloud? Verelye, as longe as suche co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueteousenes, extortyon, pillyng stryfe backebytynge, adulterye and vncleane fornycation with other innumerable fylthye vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, doo soo stronglye preuayle emonge vs, oure faythe is but a dead faythe, which the deuyll of hell hath also, and trembleth for feare. Nor we ought not, tyl <note place="margin">Iames .ii. ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> we haue cleane put awaye that olde leauen of vnpure lyfe, too come to the eatyng of our passe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouer. For then we can not dwel in Christ, nor Chryst in vs. And yf we dwell not in Christe, nor Christ in vs, we doo notte eate hys flesshe, nor drynke hys bloude, thoughe we do a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunde tymes receyue the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente of so high a thinge to
<pb facs="tcp:176398:59"/> our vtter dampnatyon. I haue now a greate cause to lamente and bewayle in my hearte, too se the people of the lower sorte, vnto whome god of his infinite goodnes, did geue the lighte of knowledge and diuyne vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standinge, in so muche that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, whiche were neuer lerned but in theyr mother ton<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gue, be able (thankes be vnto y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> heauenly spirite) too matche, yf they goo to playne scryptures, with any doctoure of the papy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes parte. I lament I say, to se howe abhomynably, the moste parte of them do lyue. Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, dronkennes, and glotony vnto them is but sporte and pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stime. They backbite, they sclan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, they chyde and stryue. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge them there is no mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, noo sobernes, no temperaū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie.
<pb facs="tcp:176398:59"/> All deceyte, all crafte, all sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiltye and falsehoode, reygneth emonge theym. Whereas yf ye heare them dyspute and reason of the scriptures and worde of god, ye wil thinke that they bee very Aungels, that bene come down from heauen. So godly they talke, so godly they speake Is not this, brethren, to mocke the gospell of our sauyour Iesu Christ, the sonne of the lyuynge God? Where be nowe the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des <note place="margin">Math. v. cha,</note> of our heauenly Master, &amp; teacher become? Let your light so shine before men, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they may se your good workes, and glori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fie your father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Marke ye now, and printe these words in your memories and mindes. We al vnto whom the heauenly father hath reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated his truthe, are bounde w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <pb facs="tcp:176398:60"/> our modest behauioure and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neste conuersation, to winne all men, if possible were, vntoo our master and sauiour Iesu Christ to stirre and moue theym, wyth our godly and vertuous liuing to laude and magnifye our hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly father. Why with honest conuersation and good works? For so is the will of god, before whom, noo vncleannes, nor fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy thing can consiste or abyde. <note place="margin">A familier simi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litude to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke all men to liue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theyr professiō</note> And besides that, as yf children be wel nurtered, behaue thē sel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues manerly and well, their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, whyche haue brough to them vp, be therfore of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonnes magnified and praysed. Whosoeuer se theym, will saye. Gods blessinge lyght vopn the heartes of suche parentes, they are worthy to haue chyldren, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen so yf we do lead here a god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:176398:60"/> &amp; vertuouse life in this world if we be sobre, modest and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til vnto al persons. Verelye it shall redound too the glorye of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> liuing god. Our father, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is in heauen, shal be gloryfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of all men. Al natyons wyll laude &amp; praise his holy and bles<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed name, yea and therby many shall be allured to the holy gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and faith of our sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>su Christ. Contrary wise, if chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drē <note place="margin">Fathers and mothers are highly discom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mēded if their chyldrē be not well brought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vp.</note> be vnnurtured &amp; vnmaner<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly behauing thē selfes rudely &amp; naught, it wil be to their paren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, great shame and dishonesty For it their fathers &amp; mothers, shal cōmonlye of all persons be dispraysed, and very muche dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended: euen soo, if we doo not liue accordyng to oure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessyon, yf oure conuersatyon, be notte honeste, decente, and
<pb facs="tcp:176398:61"/> comely, the doctrine of the gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell whyche we do professe, shal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be euill spoken vpon,. Our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye father, wythoute doubt shall be highly dishonoured, as S. Paule sayth: Thou makeste <note place="margin">Rom. ii. chapi</note> thy boste of the lawe, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the breakinge of the law, thou doest dishonoure god. For the name of the lord is euyl spo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken of, emonge the gentiles for you. Do not nowe the enemy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the truth, hauyng not one <note place="margin">What the ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myes of the truth hauyng no scripture to defende them selues, be wōt to saye.</note> syllable of the scryptures to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them selues, openly in eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry place, as they are syttyng on theyr ale benches, depredycate and saye: Where is extortyon, bryberye, and pyllynge, nowe a dayes moste vsed? Verelye e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge these newe Gospelers. Where dothe coueteousenes, whordome, adulterye, dronken<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:176398:61"/> blasphemouse swearynge and glotonye, at thys presente tyme reygne? Where, butte e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge oure newe gospellers? Who doth stryue, enuye, vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mine, one another, deceiue and begile one another. Who doth backebite and sclaunder, who is vnmercifull and vncharitable? Who (saye they) but oure newe gospellers? Thus they do saye and I beleue it partely. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dere beloued brethren, I <note place="margin">i. Peter. ii. cha</note> beseche you, as pylgrymes and straungers abstayne from flesh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye lustes, which fyghte against the soule, and see that ye haue honeste conuersatyon, emonge the enemyes of the truthe and verytye, that where as they backebyte you as euyll doers, they maye see youre good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, and prayse god in the daye
<pb facs="tcp:176398:62"/> of visitation. For so is the wyll of God, that with wel doing ye may stoppe the mouthes, of fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lysshe and ignoraunt menne, as free, and not hauing the libertie for a clooke of malycyousenes, but euen as the seruauntes of GOD. Thys verelye, wyll be vnto your owne selues, here in thys worlde, greate shame and rebuke, and in the worlde too come, vtter confusyon, if youre aduersaryes may veryfy these sayinges vpon you. Beholde, thou arte called a Chrystyan, <note place="margin">Here we do a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ude to the say<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nge of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ostle, In the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>econde to the Romaines,</note> and trustest in the gospell, and makest thy boast of GOD, and knoweste hys wyll, and allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weste thinges that be excellent and beynge enfourmed by the Gospell, beleuest that thou thy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfe arte a guyde of the blinde; a lyghte of theym whyche are
<pb facs="tcp:176398:62"/> in darkenesse, an enfourmer of theym whyche lacke des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ty on, a teacher of the vnlearned, whyche haste an exaumple of knoweledge and of the truthe, by the Gospell. Thou there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that teachest an other, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheste not thy selfe. Thou prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheste that a manne shoulde not steale, and yet thou stealeste. Thou sayest that a man should not commytte adulterye, and yet y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> breakest wedlocke. Thou abhorest idoles, and yet robbest god of his glory. For throughe breakyng the commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the gospel, wherof before al men thou makest thy boste, y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> giuest an occasion vnto al other natyons and peoples, whyche haue yet the veale of Moises, before theyr eyes, too speake e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll of the trewe doctryne and
<pb facs="tcp:176398:63"/> gospell of our Sauyoure Iesu Christ. Whych hath taught vs that we should daily in our prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers, aske, that the name of oure heauenlye father may be sainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified. Marke and vnderstand. <note place="margin">How this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titiō, halowed be thy name, ought to be vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derstanded.</note> Can hys name be holyer then it is? no forsouth. But when we saye: Holowed be thy name, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sydes all other thinges to compre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hended in thys petition, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre that of his mere mercyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, he gyue vs grace so to lyue in this wretched worlde, so too vse and behaue oure selues in our conuersatyon (all impietye and vngodlynes, which myght in any wise obscure the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his name, beyng banis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shed away) that all men, seynge oure good workes may prayse and laude his holye and blessed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Do we not then m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:176398:63"/> lie, and dissemble before god, to <note place="margin">If we liue wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kedly whē we say in our prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, halowed be thy name: we make a lie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to god.</note> our vtter destructyon and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, if we liue contrary to the same? Doubtles the lord in his fury &amp; wrath, wyl thunder out these wordes vpon vs: Ye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, why do ye preach my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, &amp; take my couenaunte in <note place="margin">Psalme .i.</note> your mouthes wheras ye ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to be refourmed, &amp; haue cast my wordes behinde you? When ye sawe a thief, ye consented vnto hym, and haue bene partakers wyth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> aduouterers. Ye haue let youre mouthes speake wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, &amp; wyth youre tongues ye haue set furth deceiptes. Ye haue sate and spoken agaynste your brethren, yea &amp; haue sclaū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dered your owne mothers son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: I wyll plucke you awaye. and there shall be none to dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you. For to him onely, that
<pb facs="tcp:176398:64"/> ordereth hys conuersation ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly, <note place="margin">To thē onlye y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> use honeste conuersatyon the saluatyon of god shal be shewed. Apocal. ii. cha It is saide vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the aungell of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church of Ephesus, I will remoue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> candlestick frō his place ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> repent. Iob .xxxiiii.</note> or according too ryghte, wyll I shewe the saluatyon of God. Besydes all these, I am greatly afrayde that he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue our candlesticke from his place, that is to say: take awaye his truth and verytye from vs, and giue vs vp into the spiryte of erroure and blindnes, where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in we haue, to the destruction of many soules, walked soo many hundreth yeres before. For god (saith the scripture) maketh the hipocrite to reygne, for the syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the people. That we may therfore, auoyde those horrible plagues, let vs repent by tyme and ordre our conuersatyon ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nestly, that we maye be accomp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted not talkers onely, but trew folowers of the gospell &amp; worde of god. Then shall our heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="tcp:176398:64"/> father, through vs, of al nati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, peoples and tonges be glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rified, praysed and magnifyed. Then without doubt shal we receiue at the lords table that blessedful and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlastynge lyfe. which is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs, with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> precious bloud of our sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uior Iesu Christ. To whome w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the father, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghost, be praise, glory and honoure, world without end.</p>
            <p>AMEN.</p>
            <p>¶ Written at Hackeney, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> laste day of October, in the yeare of our Lord. M. D. XLVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:176398:65"/>
            <p>Imprinted the .xj. day of October.</p>
            <p>Anno. Do. 1550.</p>
            <p>At Worceter by Ihon Oswen.</p>
            <p>¶ They be also to sell at Shrewesburye.</p>
            <p>❧ <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176398:65"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>